<?xml version="1.0"?>
<db:chapter xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:strings="http://exslt.org/strings" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter.architecture"><db:title>Information Architecture</db:title><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idp2113869284"><db:primary>information architecture</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idp2113869284x"><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>information architecture</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idp2113881572"><db:primary>bottom-up information architecture</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idp2113881572x"><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>bottom-up information architecture</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idp2113877220"><db:primary>top-down information architecture</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idp2113877220x"><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>top-down information architecture</db:secondary></db:indexterm>



<db:para>The overall goal of a content process it to create an effective information architecture. Information architecture is the arrangement of useful and effective content so that it can be found and navigated. An artful arrangement of awful content is of no good to anyone; information architecture is rhetoric writ large.</db:para>
<db:para>But the rhetorical nature of information architecture is often neglected. It is all too easy to think of it simply in terms of organizing things, but that can be a trap. An institution with a lot of content has its internal information finding problems to deal with, and often information architecture becomes an exercise in organizing the content for the convenience of the institution rather than the reader.</db:para>
<db:para>It is easy to think that organization is an absolute. Content is either organized or not. But this is not so. Organization is an orientation of content according to our knowledge and expectations (which is to say that organization is a form of rhetoric, as specific to its audience as any other part of rhetoric). Things are organized for us if their location, or the means of retrieving them, match what we expect and know. But what the institution (and its staff) knows and expects is very different from what the reader knows and expects. What is organization for the institution can be chaos for the reader.</db:para>
<db:para>More than this, unless content follows an organizational scheme that the reader is already familiar with, or at least makes intuitive sense in terms of what they expect and know, few readers will be likely to spend much mental energy on trying to figure out a complex organizational scheme, even one that was designed with them in mind. Instead, they will <db:indexterm><db:primary>information foraging</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>information foraging</db:secondary></db:indexterm>forage for information, which, in the Web world, means that they will use search and will follow links as long as they believe that the scent of the information they are looking for is growing stronger. For a more in-depth treatment of <db:indexterm><db:primary>information foraging</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>information foraging</db:secondary></db:indexterm>information foraging and it implications for <db:indexterm><db:primary>information architecture algorithm</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>algorithm</db:primary><db:secondary>information architecture algorithm</db:secondary></db:indexterm>information architecture, see <db:indexterm><db:primary>Every Page is Page One: Topic-based writing for Technical Communication and the Web</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>citetitle</db:primary><db:secondary>Every Page is Page One: Topic-based writing for Technical Communication and the Web</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:citetitle>Every Page is Page One: Topic-based writing for Technical Communication and the Web</db:citetitle>.)</db:para>
<db:para>It is a mistake, therefore, to think of information architecture simply in terms of organization. A building supply store organizes building materials. An architect takes those materials and uses them to construct a navigable edifice full of useful spaces with efficient passages between them. The organization and standardization of materials provided by the building supply store is highly important to the architect in their work, but organization and standardization are just starting points for the unique and useful edifice that the architect will design and build.</db:para>
<db:para>And for this reason, rhetoric is indispensable to information architecture. You can have good organization of bad material, but you cannot build a good edifice of bad material. The architect is concerned as much with the quality of their materials as they are with the design which integrates them. One does not work without the other. Information architecture is not, therefore, a wrapper around content, it is the rhetoric of the content set as a whole.</db:para>
<db:para>If there is a temptation to regard information architecture as merely a form of organization, its origins may lie in the past. For centuries, the basic unit of information was the book and the “architecture” of the book was an integral part of the responsibility of the writer and editor. Larger sets of information were created by collecting and organizing books and that was the responsibility of the librarian or bookseller.</db:para>
<db:para>Those larger collections were simply forms of organization. If there was an architecture at that scale it was in the expertise of the librarian or book seller to make inferences from the client’s needs and create useful connections.</db:para>
<db:para>With the advent of online media, first in the form of large capacity electronic media such as CD-ROMs and then the <db:indexterm><db:primary>Internet</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>media</db:primary><db:secondary>Internet</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Internet and the <db:indexterm><db:primary>Web</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>media</db:primary><db:secondary>Web</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Web, this division of responsibilities was overthrown. The basic unit of information in electronic media is not the book but the page. Thanks to <db:indexterm><db:primary>hypertext</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>media</db:primary><db:secondary>hypertext</db:secondary></db:indexterm>hypertext linking, the relationships between pages in electronic media are much more complex than on paper. Information architecture is a response to this challenge.</db:para>
<db:para>Information architect, therefore, is not merely a new name for librarian, but the integration of roles that were formerly divided, or, rather, the result of a very different partitioning of roles in the content process. Often the process changes we make to support rhetoric involve partitioning certain forms of content complexity away from writers and directing it to information architects. But this is not just about relieving writers of a burden, it is also about giving the information architect the visibility into and control over rhetoric that they need to do their job. By no means does this transfer all control of rhetoric from writer to information architect, for the information architect does not have the intimate knowledge of the subject matter to define rhetorical best practices for every type of content. Rather it means that writer and information architect must work together to define and implement those best practices at all scales of the content set.</db:para>
<db:para>Another way in which things are different today is that the architecture of online media has to account for the ability to add, modify, and delete individual bits of content at any time. It is possible to think of book or library architectures in largely static terms. It is a serious mistake to think of Web architectures as static.</db:para>
<db:para>This leads to the development of architectures of much smaller units with much more complex relationships to a much larger, more diverse, and more rapidly changing set of resources. These architectures include not only text and static graphics but active media: videos, animation, and dynamic feeds and information widgets. Given these factors, the old separation of roles between writer and librarian no longer works. Unless we find a way to partition the responsibility away from them, writers now have to be much more conscious of how their pages interact with other pages in the collection, including those created by others. The scale at which these small pieces of content relate with each other is much greater than the scale at which the pieces of a book related to each other. This constitutes a significant increase in complexity (more, and more difficult, decisions requiring greater knowledge or skill) and calls for a whole new approach to information architecture, and for the appearance of a function and a role that had no equivalent in the paper world.</db:para>
<db:para>However, information architecture still needs to support paper delivery of content, and to ensure that the design of content delivered on paper is as effective as it can be. In many case, content delivered on paper will be the same content that was delivered on the Web and will come from the same repository. However, if the roles of writer and information architect have been partitioned to support Web output, responsibility for paper output is also likely to fall to the information architect, and structured writing algorithms such as <db:indexterm><db:primary>differential single sourcing</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>algorithm</db:primary><db:secondary>differential single sourcing</db:secondary></db:indexterm>differential single sourcing are likely to become an important part of the information architect’s concerns.</db:para>
<db:para>As noted above, in many cases we use structured writing to transfer complexity from the writer to the information architect. It is the vast increase in the complexity of information architecture that makes this transfer necessary. But it also points out how much information needs to pass from the writer to the information architect for the information architect to do their job and not let any of the complexity slip through the cracks. Correct partitioning is essential to success in this area.</db:para>
<db:section>
<db:title>Top-down vs. bottom-up information architecture</db:title>
<db:para>In looking at information architecture as a form of rhetoric, it is useful to start by making a basic distinction between two types of information architecture: <db:indexterm><db:primary>top-down information architecture</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>top-down information architecture</db:secondary></db:indexterm>top-down and <db:indexterm><db:primary>bottom-up information architecture</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>bottom-up information architecture</db:secondary></db:indexterm>bottom-up. Top down information architecture deals with navigational aids and organizing systems that stand apart from the content and point to it. A table of contents or a website menu system is a piece of top-down information architecture. Bottom-up information architecture deals with navigation and organization that exists within the content itself. A web site with a consistent approach to <db:indexterm><db:primary>hypertext</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>media</db:primary><db:secondary>hypertext</db:secondary></db:indexterm>hypertext <db:indexterm><db:primary>links</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>structure</db:primary><db:secondary>links</db:secondary></db:indexterm>links within its pages is an example of a bottom-up information architecture.</db:para>
<db:para>But <db:indexterm><db:primary>bottom-up information architecture</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>bottom-up information architecture</db:secondary></db:indexterm>bottom-up information architecture is not just about linking, it is about the way content is written. A page in a bottom-up information architecture is designed to be entered via search or links from almost anywhere (as opposed to being designed to be entered exclusively from a previous chapter). But it is also designed to help readers with onward navigation, to be a hub of its local subject space, offering readers many onward vectors according to their needs and interests.</db:para>
<db:para>This is a very different approach to information design because it makes navigation an integral part of the rhetoric of a document and the content set into which it is integrated. Linking is not an afterthought, but part of the rhetorical design of the document. We are no longer dealing with an architecture in which navigation takes the reader to content and leaves them there. Navigation and rhetoric are intertwined and continuous.</db:para>
<db:para>I call this approach to information design <db:indexterm><db:primary>Every Page is Page One</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>Every Page is Page One</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Every Page is Page One, and it is described in my book, <db:indexterm><db:primary>Every Page is Page One: Topic-based Writing for Technical Communication and the Web</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>citetitle</db:primary><db:secondary>Every Page is Page One: Topic-based Writing for Technical Communication and the Web</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:citetitle>Every Page is Page One: Topic-based Writing for Technical Communication and the Web</db:citetitle>. One of the key principles of Every Page is Page One is that a <db:indexterm><db:primary>topic</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>structure</db:primary><db:secondary>topic</db:secondary></db:indexterm>topic should follow a well defined <db:indexterm><db:primary>rhetorical structure</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>structure</db:primary><db:secondary>rhetorical structure</db:secondary></db:indexterm>rhetorical structure or type. Structured writing, particularly <db:indexterm><db:primary>subject-domain</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>subject-domain</db:secondary></db:indexterm>subject-domain structured writing, is very useful in developing Every Page is Page One content.</db:para>
<db:para>Bottom-up and top-down information architectures are not incompatible with each other. In fact almost every information architecture has both top-down and bottom-up elements. (Books, for instance, which are principally top-down, based on a table of contents, may also have internal cross references, which are a bottom up mechanism.)</db:para>
<db:para>Structured writing can be used to drive both the <db:indexterm><db:primary>top-down information architecture</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>top-down information architecture</db:secondary></db:indexterm>top-down and <db:indexterm><db:primary>bottom-up information architecture</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>bottom-up information architecture</db:secondary></db:indexterm>bottom-up aspects of information architecture.</db:para>
<db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idp2113869284"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idp2113881572"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idp2113877220"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idp2113869284x"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idp2113881572x"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idp2113877220x"/></db:section>
</db:chapter>
