<?xml version="1.0"?>
<db:chapter xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:strings="http://exslt.org/strings" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter.writing"><db:title>Writing</db:title><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idm68988316"><db:primary>writing</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idm68988316x"><db:primary>algorithm</db:primary><db:secondary>writing</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idm68988572"><db:primary>functional lucidity</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idm68988572x"><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>functional lucidity</db:secondary></db:indexterm>



<db:para>Most of the complexity of the content process flows through the writer. Before computers, the writer prepared a typescript which was handed off to other people to manipulate before the work was eventually set in type and printed. Today, we generally expect that the writer will be the last person to manually change or manipulate content. Everything after that will be handled by an algorithm. The content the writer writes has to contain everything the publishing process needs to complete successfully. Making that manageable for writers is key to successfully partitioning your content system.</db:para>
<db:para>But the complexity imposed by publishing and content management functions is not the only source of complexity that writers must deal with. Developing the best rhetorical strategy for a given subject matter and applying it consistently, as well as working effectively with other writers to achieve the overall content strategy of the organization are also major sources of complexity, and all that complexity flows through the writer as well.</db:para>
<db:para>If we are going to partition the content system to relieve writers of as many extended decisions as possible, we will need to create structures that effectively direct those decisions away from them. But we can’t do this by creating a loose unconstrained environment for writers. If we don’t get a high level of conformance to specific content structures, our algorithms will not be reliable, the partitioning will break down, and the complexity will fall back on the writers or down to the readers. The structures we present to writers must combine strict conformance with ease of use. In all our planning of structures and algorithms, therefore, we have to keep the question of how easy this is going to be for the writer squarely in the forefront.</db:para>
<db:para>In media-domain systems like word processors and desktop publishing systems, the writer is asked to decide about formatting structures while writing. One of the traditional arguments for structured writing is to relieve the writer of the burden of making and executing formatting decisions so they can focus on writing. This means moving to the document domain. But in the document domain, the writer has a new set of structures to think about. Is it easier on the writer to think about and manipulate document domain structures rather than media domain structures? In some cases, yes. For instance, writing a blog post or a web page in <db:indexterm><db:primary>MarkDown</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>MarkDown</db:secondary></db:indexterm>MarkDown may be less cumbersome for some writers than using a <db:indexterm><db:primary>WYSIWYG</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>WYSIWYG</db:secondary></db:indexterm>WYSIWYG <db:indexterm><db:primary>HTML</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>HTML</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>HTML</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>standard</db:primary><db:secondary>HTML</db:secondary></db:indexterm>HTML editor.</db:para>
<db:para>However, <db:indexterm><db:primary>Markdown</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>Markdown</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Markdown does not contain enough structure, or enough constraints on its structure, to enable many of the structured writing algorithms we will be looking at. If we want to support these algorithms, we will need something more structured.</db:para>
<db:para>If we are proposing to implement management-intensive algorithms, such as <db:indexterm><db:primary>content reuse algorithm</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>algorithm</db:primary><db:secondary>content reuse algorithm</db:secondary></db:indexterm>content reuse, writers may need to learn and manipulate an entire management system and the management policies that the organization puts in place around it. Depending on how complex these policies are and how foreign they are to the writer’s experience, this can create a burden far greater than that of creating and manipulating formatting according to a style guide.</db:para>
<db:para>We could look at this and say, okay, yes, writing is now more difficult and more complex than it was before because of all this additional structure, but we are getting additional advantages as well, such as reuse and content management. The problem is, attention is a finite resource. Writing is a task that takes full attention, so any decision making added to the task takes attention away from writing, as well as requiring more knowledge and skill on the part of the writer. As writing get more difficult, writers do all of the component tasks less well, and the fewer writers can contribute at all. The more of the writer’s attention is required on structure, the less is available for writing, and the quality of the writing suffers.</db:para>
<db:para>As the quality of the writing suffers, the writer becomes frustrated with the system, and becomes more interested in getting their ideas down than in obeying the onerous structural rules that are getting in their way. When that happens, the quality of the structure suffers as well. And if both the quality of the writing and the quality of the structures decline, all of your algorithms become less reliable, compromising all of benefits you hoped to obtain. Too much complexity dumped on any one person or process compromises all downstream persons and processes.</db:para>
<db:para>Conformance is fundamentally a human activity. It is that writer who must conform. Good conformance results from creating structures that are easy to conform to. It all begins with writing. Unfortunately, writing is often the last thing people think about in designing content management and structured writing systems. It is the place that complexity get dumped before it eventually gets dumped on readers.</db:para>
<db:para>One of the most familiar tropes of the content management industry is that problems with content management systems are not technology problems, they are human problems. The solution, this trope suggests, lies in better change management and more training. The presumption here is that the tools work fine if only you give them correct input. If the input is not correct, that is the fault of the humans who created the input. But this is an argument we would not accept for any other kind of system. For any other kind of system we would say, “this system is too hard to use”, not “the problem is everybody needs to be better trained and more accepting of change”. The real fault here is poor system design. If humans cannot conform to the structures that the system requires, the fault is in the system design. It is not partitioning and distributing complexity correctly. The structures should be redesigned to be easier to conform to. (We will look at this in more detail in <db:xref linkend="chapter.conformance"/>.)</db:para>
<db:para>How is designing structures for ease of writing consistent with designing them to match the specific constraints that we want to impose for the sake of quality and efficient processing? As we have seen, moving from the <db:indexterm><db:primary>media domain</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>media domain</db:secondary></db:indexterm>media domain to the <db:indexterm><db:primary>document domain</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>document domain</db:secondary></db:indexterm>document domain allows us to factor out or impose certain structural constraints, but often requires the introduction of the management domain to impose content management constraints. These complexities detract from ease of writing. But we have also seen that by moving to the subject domain we can factor out many of the document domain and management domain structures. Designing structures for writing, therefore, often consists of factoring out complex publishing and content management structures using subject-domain structures that are lucid for writers.</db:para>
<db:para>One of the most important consequences of this, both for ease of writing and reliability of data, is that in the subject domain you are not asking the writer to think, to decide, and to structure content, in terms of algorithms. In this sense, the move to the subject domain not only factors out specific constraints from the writer, it factors out the need to think in algorithms at all, leaving the writer free to think and decide in terms of subject matter. This freedom to focus on content is a property I call functional lucidity.</db:para>
<db:section>
<db:title>Functional lucidity</db:title>
<db:para>Functional lucidity refers to the total intellectual burden that a system imposes on a writer when they are in the actual process of composition. How clearly do they understand all that is being asked of them, and how fluidly and naturally can they create all the structures and content that are required. The functional lucidity of a markup language is not a matter of its size or its complexity. It is a matter of how natural and obvious it seems to the writer as they are using it. It is a matter, also, of how much it aligns with their core decisions, the decisions that are essential to the task, as opposed to extended decisions, which are external to it.</db:para>
<db:para>If you are asked to add markup to your content as you write, if you are asked to shape your content according to the constraints that a structured writing language dictates, then the lucidity of that markup and the structures it defines are vital to your success. The names of the structures, the order in which they occur should spring into your mind as readily (if not more so) that the words and phrases and ideas you are trying to record. They should come to you are a consequence of your core decisions, the decisions you have to make anyway.</db:para>
<db:para>If you have ever tried to learn a language, you know how painful it is to write even a paragraph in a language you are not fluent in. The effort of finding words and correct grammatical structures takes all of the attention that should be reserved for what you are trying to say. Writing in a markup language where the structures don’t make intuitive sense, where they don’t seem to fit the thoughts you are trying to express, where they require knowledge and skills external to your core task, is very much like this. Lucidity is essential to avoid having the markup absorb all of the attention that should be focused on the content.</db:para>
<db:para>Functional lucidity is not an absolute property, of course. What is lucid for one writer may be opaque to another. In particular, professional technical writers who have been used to writing in structured <db:indexterm><db:primary>document domain</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>document domain</db:secondary></db:indexterm>document domain templates in applications like FrameMaker may find a markup language like <db:indexterm><db:primary>DocBook</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>DocBook</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>DocBook</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>standard</db:primary><db:secondary>DocBook</db:secondary></db:indexterm>DocBook functionally lucid, whereas someone not used to thinking in these terms would find it difficult and distracting. On the other hand, those writers used to FrameMaker often find DITA’s structure difficult to get used to because they do not find its approach to topics lucid. To still others it seems very natural. Often this is a matter of how the extended decisions required by the new tool align with those required by the old tool, decisions that the writer is already accustomed to making.</db:para>
<db:para>But while different writers may have different degrees of experience and familiarity with abstract document structures, all writers should have familiarity with the subject matter they are writing about. Thus a well-designed <db:indexterm><db:primary>subject domain</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>subject domain</db:secondary></db:indexterm>subject domain language tends to naturally have functional lucidity for everyone who is likely to use it.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>Simplicity and Clarity</db:title>
<db:para>One of the biggest benefits of subject domain markup for writers is a much higher degree of functional lucidity compared with a typical document domain language.</db:para>
<db:para>While a general document domain language like <db:indexterm><db:primary>DocBook</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>DocBook</db:secondary></db:indexterm>DocBook needs to have a wide range of document structures, a recipe markup language such as we developed in <db:xref linkend="chapter.subject-domain"/>, has only a few simple structures. Better still, there are very few permutations of those structures. The decisions it requires the writer to make align closely with the core task of expressing the method for preparing a dish.</db:para>
<db:para>Because subject domain structures describe the subject matter they contain, they are also much clearer to writers, who may not understand complex document structures (or, more often, the subtle distinctions between several similar document structures), but who do (we hope) understand their subject matter.</db:para>
<db:para>The combination of simplicity and clarity mean that in many cases you can get writers to create subject-domain structured content with little or no training. For instance, even if we add some additional fields to our recipe markup, you could still hand a sample like the one below to an writer and ask them to follow it as a template, without giving them any training or any special tools.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="sam">
recipe: Hard Boiled Egg
    introduction:
        A hard boiled egg is simple and nutritious.
    ingredients:: ingredient, quantity
        eggs, 12
        water, 2qt
    preparation:
        1. Place eggs in pan and cover with water.
        2. Bring water to a boil.
        3. Remove from heat and cover for 12 minutes.
        4. Place eggs in cold water to stop cooking.
        5. Peel and serve.
    prep-time: 15 minutes
    serves: 6
    wine-match: champagne and orange juice
    beverage-match: orange juice
    nutrition:
        serving: 1 large (50 g)
        calories: 78
        total-fat: 5 g
        saturated-fat: 0.7 g
        polyunsaturated-fat: 0.7 g    
        monounsaturated-fat: 2 g    
        cholesterol: 186.5 mg    
        sodium: 62 mg    
        potassium: 63 mg    
        total-carbohydrate: 0.6 g    
        dietary-fiber: 0 g    
        sugar: 0.6 g    
        protein: 6 g    
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Of course, the downside is that recipe markup is only good for one thing: recipes. Complexity is never destroyed, only moved somewhere else. So this approach moves complexity away from the writer to the person who has to design and maintain these structures and the algorithms that process them. (<db:indexterm><db:primary>Information Architect</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>role</db:primary><db:secondary>Information Architect</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Information Architect and <db:indexterm><db:primary>Content Engineer</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>role</db:primary><db:secondary>Content Engineer</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Content Engineer are both titles sometimes used for the person with this responsibility.)</db:para>
<db:para>This can seen scary because we are not used to partitioning complexity in this way. But then, we also recognize that the way we have partitioned complexity in the past has not been as successful as we would like – that it has, in fact, left much of the complexity of content creation unhandled, resulting in that complexity being dumped on our readers. If a new partitioning of the complexity of the content creation process is required, we have to accept that some of these new methods of partitioning will be unfamiliar. They are the place where previously unhandled complexity that used to get dumped on the reader is now being handled.</db:para>
<db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm68988316"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm68988572"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm68988316x"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm68988572x"/></db:section>
</db:chapter>
