<?xml version="1.0"?>
<db:chapter xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:strings="http://exslt.org/strings" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter.constraints"><db:title>Constraint Languages</db:title><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idm2118487180"><db:primary>constraints</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idm2118487180x"><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>constraints</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idm2118487052"><db:primary>constraint languages</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idm2118487052x"><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>constraint languages</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idm2118483468"><db:primary>XML Schema</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idm2118483468x"><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>XML Schema</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idm2118485644"><db:primary>Schematron</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idm2118485644x"><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>Schematron</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" significance="preferred" xml:id="idm2118485772"><db:primary>Relax NG</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idm2118485772x"><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>Relax NG</db:secondary></db:indexterm>



<db:para>Structured writing is about applying constraints to content and recording the constraints that the content follows, both to constrain what writers write and to constrain how algorithms interpret the content. This requires some way to express constraints in a formal and machine readable way. Schema languages partition this problem and redirect it to a common validation algorithm expressed by a standard piece of software that everyone can use. Schema languages are, quite simply, languages for expressing constraints.</db:para>
<db:para>For a <db:indexterm><db:primary>concrete markup languages</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>concrete markup languages</db:secondary></db:indexterm>concrete markup languages like MarkDown, the content constraints are established in the code of the MarkDown processor. They are validated when the processor parses the MarkDown file. (In practice, though, MarkDown does no meaningful validation. Anything it does not recognize as markup, it simply outputs as text.)</db:para>
<db:para>For <db:indexterm><db:primary>abstract markup languages</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>concept</db:primary><db:secondary>abstract markup languages</db:secondary></db:indexterm>abstract markup languages like XML you define structures yourself. Basic XML syntax is validated by the parser, but the definition of constraints is the business of a schema language. The validation of those constraints is the business of a piece of software called a “validator”.</db:para>
<db:para>A schema language is a structured language for defining structured languages. The schema for a markup languages says what structures are allowed and in what order and relationship. A given document either conforms to those constraints or it does not.</db:para>
<db:para>Here is an example of a schema in a schema language called <db:indexterm><db:primary>RelaxNG</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>RelaxNG</db:secondary></db:indexterm>RelaxNG, which is one of several schema languages available for defining <db:indexterm><db:primary>XML</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>XML</db:secondary></db:indexterm>XML-based markup languages:<db:footnote><db:para>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RELAX_NG#XML_syntax</db:para></db:footnote></db:para>
<db:programlisting language="RNG">

&lt;element name="book" xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"&gt;
   &lt;oneOrMore&gt;
      &lt;element name="page"&gt;
         &lt;text/&gt;
      &lt;/element&gt;
   &lt;/oneOrMore&gt;
&lt;/element&gt;
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>This example defines two elements and three constraints. The first element is called <db:code>book</db:code> and the second is called <db:code>page</db:code>. The constraints are:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The <db:code>page</db:code> element must occur inside the <db:code>book</db:code> element. (Because the <db:code>page</db:code> element is defined inside the <db:code>book</db:code> element structure.)</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>There must be at least one <db:code>page</db:code> element inside the <db:code>book</db:code> element, and there can be more. (Because the <db:code>page</db:code> element is defined inside an RNG <db:code>oneOrMore</db:code> element.)</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Text can occur inside the <db:code>page</db:code> element, but not directly inside the <db:code>book</db:code> element. (Because the RNG <db:code>text</db:code> element occurs inside the definition of the <db:code>page</db:code> element, but not as a direct child of the <db:code>book</db:code> element definition.)</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>Thus if an author wrote:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="xml">

&lt;book&gt;Moby Dick
    &lt;page&gt;Call me Ishmael. Some years ago- never mind how long 
    precisely- having little or no money in my purse, and nothing 
    particular to interest me on shore, I thought I would sail 
    about a little and see the watery part of the world.&lt;/page&gt;
&lt;/book&gt;
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>the validator would report an error because the words “Moby Dick” are directly inside the book element and text is not allowed in that position.</db:para>
<db:para>There are several different schema languages for XML each of which is capable of expressing and enforcing different sets of constraints. It is not unusual to combine different schema languages to more completely constrain a markup language. In particular, it is not uncommon to use a schema language called <db:indexterm><db:primary>Schematron</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>Schematron</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Schematron in concert with other schema languages like <db:indexterm><db:primary>RelaxNG</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>RelaxNG</db:secondary></db:indexterm>RNG or <db:indexterm><db:primary>XSD</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>XSD</db:secondary></db:indexterm>XSD. While most schema languages work by modeling the structure of a document, as in the <db:indexterm><db:primary>RelaxNG</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>RelaxNG</db:secondary></db:indexterm>RNG example above, <db:indexterm><db:primary>Schematron</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>Schematron</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Schematron works by making assertions about the structure in a language called <db:indexterm><db:primary>XPath</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>XPath</db:secondary></db:indexterm>XPath. A <db:indexterm><db:primary>Schematron</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>Schematron</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Schematron schema would make a lousy guide for authoring, but it can test assertions, and therefore enforce constraints, that no other schema language can.</db:para>
<db:para>Here is a simple <db:indexterm><db:primary>Schematron</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>Schematron</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Schematron example. It defines one of the constraints listed above, namely that a book element must contain at least one page element.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="schematron">

&lt;schema xmlns="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"  
 queryBinding="xslt2"&gt;
    &lt;pattern&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Book constraint&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;rule context="book"&gt;
            &lt;assert test="page"&gt;A book must contain at 
            least one page.&lt;/assert&gt;
        &lt;/rule&gt;
    &lt;/pattern&gt;
&lt;/schema&gt;
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The rule says that in the context of the element <db:code>book</db:code> the assertion that there is an element <db:code>page</db:code> must be true. If it is not, the message within the <db:code>assert</db:code> element will be displayed.</db:para>
<db:para>In the <db:indexterm><db:primary>RelaxNG</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>RelaxNG</db:secondary></db:indexterm>RNG schema example, the schema is essentially a template that models the hierarchy of the document. The constraints are consequences of the structure of that hierarchy. (The <db:code>book</db:code> element cannot contain text because there is no place for text in that part of the hierarchy.) Only documents that conform to the template are valid.</db:para>
<db:para>In the <db:indexterm><db:primary>Schematron</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>Schematron</db:secondary></db:indexterm>Schematron example, the schema is a series of constraint statements. The hierarchy of the document is a consequence of meeting all the constraints. Any document is valid as long as it conforms to all the stated constraints.</db:para>
<db:para>There are essentially two ways to describe constraints. One is to start from the basis that nothing is allowed unless there is a specific rule allows it. The other is to start from the basis that everything is allowed unless there is some specific rule that forbids it. Schematron is based on the latter doctrine. It says anything is valid as long as it passes a given set of tests. Other schema languages take the former approach. If you validate an XML document against an empty XSD schema, for instance, the validator will say it is invalid because it can’t find the definition of the root element. In essence, therefore, their constraints are described as a set of permissions. The writer is then constrained to stay within the boundaries of what is permitted.</db:para>
<db:para>Starting on the basis that everything is allowed is not generally a good model for structured writing. You have to write algorithms that can handle everything that is included in a document, so you pretty much have to start with a definitive list of what is allowed and in what combinations. This is why Schematron is seldom used as a standalone schema language. But it can be very useful for qualifying the use of certain structures permitted by other in other schema languages, in particular the kinds of constraints that cannot be expressed in the main schema language.</db:para>
<db:para>The wider point here are that there are many occasions in the course of writing and publishing content in which to express and enforce constraints. Some constraints can only be expressed during the publishing process, for instance. An example would be the resolution of a <db:indexterm><db:primary>key</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>structure</db:primary><db:secondary>key</db:secondary></db:indexterm>key reference. We can only tell if there is a value or resource corresponding to the key when the <db:indexterm><db:primary>synthesis algorithm</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>algorithm</db:primary><db:secondary>synthesis algorithm</db:secondary></db:indexterm>synthesis algorithm is compete and all the elements of the published content set are assembled and resolved.</db:para>
<db:para>Constraint, therefore, is not something that exists at a single point in the writing and publishing process. It is something you need to consider across the entire publishing process design. In particular, when errors occur at any point in the publishing process, you should trace them back to the point where the constraint that could have prevented them was violated, and ask how that constraint could have been better implemented or enforced.</db:para>
<db:para>One of the most basic design principles of any process is that errors should be caught as early in the process as possible, and that any error-prone process should be designed to make errors less likely. Factoring out constraints by moving content to a different domain, as we have noted several times, is an excellent way to reduce errors in structured writing, and to ensure that errors are caught earlier in the process.</db:para>
<db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118487180"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118487052"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118483468"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118485644"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118485772"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118487180x"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118487052x"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118483468x"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118485644x"/><db:indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idm2118485772x"/></db:chapter>
