<?xml version="1.0"?>
<db:partintro xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:strings="http://exslt.org/strings">

<db:para>If structured writing is a system for partitioning a document into a set of pieces, then what tools do you use and what kinds of pieces do you partition a document into?</db:para>
<db:para>The most common tool for partitioning is <db:indexterm><db:primary>markup</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>tool</db:primary><db:secondary>markup</db:secondary></db:indexterm>markup, which is essentially a means for partitioning a document into the raw content (text, images, and media; anything the reader consumes) and the structures and instructions that govern how that content will be delivered to the reader. <db:indexterm><db:primary>HTML</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>language</db:primary><db:secondary>HTML</db:secondary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>HTML</db:primary></db:indexterm><db:indexterm><db:primary>standard</db:primary><db:secondary>HTML</db:secondary></db:indexterm>HTML is an example of a markup language that you may have worked with. I will look at the mechanics of markup languages in <db:xref linkend="chapter.markup"/>.</db:para>
<db:para>Markup languages partition documents by breaking them up into pieces and naming those pieces in various ways. In this section, I introduce four domains of content structure that represent four fundamentally different ways of partitioning a document. Those domains are: media, document, subject, and management. None of these domains is new. People have been using these approaches to markup for decades. Dividing these techniques into domains simply gives us a consistent way to talk about them and explore the virtues of each. Through the rest of the book I will show how choosing a markup language in each of these domains profoundly affects how you can partition your content system.</db:para>
<db:blockquote>
<db:para>Note: The term <db:emphasis>semantic</db:emphasis> is commonly used to characterize markup languages. Semantics is the study of meaning, so semantic markup is markup that tells us what the content means. Unfortunately, people can, and do, understand the phrase “semantic markup” in different ways, leading to confusion about what is and is not semantic markup. Therefore, I do not use the term semantic to describe markup languages, though I do use it in other contexts.</db:para>
</db:blockquote>
</db:partintro>
