<?xml version="1.0"?>
<db:chapter xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:strings="http://exslt.org/strings" version="5.0" xml:id="introduction"><db:title>Introduction</db:title>

<db:para>There are only six reasons for an organization to create content:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>To meet regulatory requirements</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>To ensure the correct performance of internal processes</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>To generate leads and support the sales process</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>To lobby governments and affect social and political trends</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>To improve customer retention through post-sales support</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>To deliver content as a product in its own right</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>Each of these goes straight to the bottom line of revenue and profitability, and each depends directly on the quality of content. To create a content process with any goal in mind other than to maximize content quality is foolish, shortsighted, and almost certainly guaranteed to have negative effects on revenue and profitability even if it reduces costs in a particular division.</db:para>
<db:para>Rhetoric is the way in which content works to meet its goals. Each of the content goals outlined above requires a specific approach to rhetoric to make sure it does the job it is supposed to do. At the same time, like any business function, the creation of content needs to be done efficiently and it needs to meet its deadlines. To achieve your business goals, you need great rhetoric and efficient process.</db:para>
<db:section>
<db:title>Rhetoric</db:title>
<db:para>Aristotle defined rhetoric as “the faculty of observing in any given case the available means of persuasion”. To put it another way, rhetoric is figuring out what to say and how to say it to persuade, inform, entertain, or enable the reader to act.</db:para>
<db:para>The word rhetoric is sometimes used dismissively, to describe content that is hollow or empty of meaning: “mere rhetoric”. And content can certainly use all kinds of rhetorical tricks while entirely lacking substance. But if there can be mere rhetoric there can also be substantive rhetoric, and if you want to communicate your substance effectively, you need sound rhetoric. Rhetoric without substance lacks value. Substance without rhetoric hides value. Substance plus rhetoric unlocks value.</db:para>
<db:para>Rhetoric takes many forms. In some cases it is a matter of choosing the right metaphor to get across an individual point, or the word that triggers a particular emotional reaction. But there are much more mundane aspects to rhetoric as well, such as making sure you give the right information, making sure you use the right terms, making sure the content is organized and labeled so people can find what they need. These are all just as essential to persuading, informing, entertaining, or enabling the reader to act, and usually more so. They are just as much part of rhetoric as <db:emphasis>le mot juste</db:emphasis> or the striking metaphor.</db:para>
<db:para>These more mundane aspects of rhetoric are often quite structured, which means that they are more or less repeatable. To say that something is structured is to say that it conforms to a some shape or set of rules that we can observe, define, and reproduce independent of the particular instance, and thus that we can create many instances of things that all conform to the same structure.</db:para>
<db:para>A house is made of a particular set of bricks, but the bricks are put together according to an architectural plan – a structure that can be reproduced next door using different bricks conforming to the same architecture. A recipe is made of particular words, but those words are organized according to a rhetorical plan – a structure than can be reproduced on the next page using different words (describing a different dish) but following the same rhetorical plan. Structured writing, in the purely rhetorical sense of the word, means capturing, defining and implementing repeatable rhetorical structures.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>Process</db:title>
<db:para>This ability to repeat structure is at the heart of process in any field. A process finds and defines the most efficient way to do something, which is pointless unless you plan to do the same thing more than once. Writing down how to do something you never plan to do again would serve no purpose. Process is all about repetition. A process that aims to produce rhetoric is therefore fundamentally concerned with the repeatability of rhetoric. Thus process and rhetoric are intimately combined in the production of content, and structured writing holds the key to repeatability in rhetoric and process.</db:para>
<db:para>Too often, structured writing systems and implementations focus on process issues alone, leaving rhetoric to take care of itself. But there are three problems with this approach:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Rhetoric is a complex task requiring the whole of the writer’s attention. Yet many of the tools designed to support process goals such as publishing and reuse introduce numerous complex tasks and concepts into the writer’s environment, pulling attention away from the rhetoric that ought to be their chief concern. This book will show how you can remove most of these distractions from writers using the right techniques.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Some of the structures and processes enforced to meet process goals can be actively harmful to rhetoric. They may make the process more efficient, but at the price of preventing writers from producing the best rhetoric, thereby reducing the quality and effectiveness of content. Fortunately, as this book will show, there are structured writing techniques that can achieve most of the same process goals without harming rhetoric, or while actively improving it. In many cases they also improve the process as well.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>There are large deficits in rhetoric in many content sets that exist because producing first class, thorough, consistent rhetoric is a difficult task in its own right. (The principal cause of this is the Curse of Knowledge, a concept I will explore in <db:xref linkend="chapter.writing"/>). This book will show how structured writing techniques can be used to address the difficulties and complexities of creating good rhetoric consistently across a body of content.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>Process and rhetoric, therefore, should never be treated independently of each other. The whole purpose of the content process is to produce good rhetoric. It is, if you like, a rhetorical process. Process and rhetoric are too intimately connected to hope to successfully treat one while ignoring the other.</db:para>
<db:para>This cuts both ways, of course. The things you do to support rhetoric must also be compatible with or contribute to efficient process. An approach to rhetoric that brings your production schedule to a halt is not doing anyone any good. Indeed, timeliness has become one of the key attributes of good rhetoric today. Readers expect information be to available when they need it and to be continually up to date. If your process cannot produce good rhetoric in a timely manner, it is not producing good rhetoric at all.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>Complexity</db:title>
<db:para>The chief impediment to a process producing good rhetoric is complexity. Creating content is a complex business. There are rhetorical issues:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>You have to research your subject matter and your audience.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>You have to figure out what to say and how to say it to persuade, inform, entertain, or enable your reader to act.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>And there are process issues:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>You then have to record the content, manage it, and publish it, potentially to many different audiences and many different media.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>If your organization creates a lot of content, you have to coordinate with everyone else creating content and make sure it all works together and serves the organization’s goals.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>As your subject matter and your business needs change, you need to figure out how your content needs to change and implement those changes cleanly and efficiently.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>You have to create good consistent letter shapes with your pen.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>Okay, we haven’t had to deal with that last one for a while now. But something has to create letter shapes, line them up nicely, and fit them within the margins. Before we had machines to do it for us, that task was part of the writer’s life and an essential skill if you wanted to create a readable document. And if you wanted more than one copy, you had to write out each copy by hand or hire copyists to do it for you.</db:para>
<db:para>Fortunately, Gutenberg invented a machine that took that burden off the writer’s hands, making the writer’s life easier. The printing press allowed people who were not trained in calligraphy to become writers. It also put a lot of copyists out of business. (Yes, the loss of white-collar jobs to automation is not a new thing.) But it also made books much cheaper, revolutionizing civilization and creating many more white-collar jobs.</db:para>
<db:para>The forming of letter shapes and making copies is part of the content creation process. As long as writers had to perform these tasks, they needed a particular set of skills and a great deal of time in order to create a new work. Following the introduction of the printing press many more new works were created. These basic process improvements had a profound impact on rhetoric, freeing time and energy for the creation of new rhetoric.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>Partitioning complexity</db:title>
<db:para>Process improvement of this kind can be described as a partitioning of a task or process. The printing press partitioned the task of physical book making from the task of language composition, thus freeing writers to spend more time and energy writing.</db:para>
<db:para>Of course, the writer’s handwriting still had to be good enough for the printer to read. But then came the typewriter, the computer keyboard, and the touch screen with predictive typing, and now many children are not even being taught cursive writing in school. Lament the withering of handwriting skills if you like, but it represents a new partitioning of the writing process, one in which manipulating a pen and shaping letters has been entirely partitioned from the writer.</db:para>
<db:para>Of course, this introduces a new skill that the writer has to master: typing. When a task is partitioned, there is always a new skill to learn. Partitioning a task creates the need to transmit information from one partition to another. Typewriters (or, today, the computer and monitor) take over the task of forming letters on paper or screen, but they need to know which letters the writer wants. The writer tells them by tapping keys on the keyboard. The keys are the interface between the partitions of the writing system. Using new interfaces is part of adapting to the newly partitioned system.</db:para>
<db:para>Structured writing  allows us to partition the content production process by capturing information that must be passed from one partition to another. For instance, it can partition the creation of a list from the formatting of a list by using list markup (such as HTML <db:code>&lt;ol&gt;</db:code> and <db:code>&lt;li&gt;</db:code> tags) and a separate formatting language (such as CSS) to specify how list are formatted. The markup language serves as the interface between the writing partition and the formatting partition, ensuring that the required information – this is a list, this is a list item – gets passed from one partition to another.</db:para>
<db:para>By partitioning the process in the right way, we can separate tasks that require complex skills and knowledge among different workers, allowing each to develop and practice their individual expertise while ensuring the all the pieces come together at the end in a reliable and efficient manner.</db:para>
<db:para>Every content organization partitions and distributes content creation. Newspapers do not make reporters drive delivery trucks. Publishing houses do not let authors design book covers (much as they might want to). Recognizing that spotting your own mistakes is difficult, wise organizations partition the job of editing and proofreading content from the job of writing it. When they need to orchestrate a large body of content to the Web, organizations employ information architects and content strategists. All of these examples partition the complexity of the content process to improve quality and efficiency. Partitioning a modern content process is complex, often involving multiple partitions with multiple complex interfaces.</db:para>
<db:para>There are two potential benefits to partitioning the content process. First, it can make the writer’s job easier, meaning that more people can write, and writers can focus more attention on subject matter and rhetoric and less on the tools. Second, you can improve efficiency by assigning partitioned tasks to people or processes better equipped to handle them. A typewriter or a computer makes much more consistent letter shapes than a human hand. The printing press makes identical copies much faster than a human copyist.</db:para>
<db:sidebar role="pullquote">
<db:para>You can’t reduce the fundamental complexity of content creation.</db:para>
</db:sidebar>
<db:para>You can’t reduce the fundamental complexity of content creation. All that stuff has to get done, and it is all difficult in one way or another. Different tasks require different skills and knowledge. Rhetoric alone – figuring out what to say and how best to say it – is a complex task that deserves the writer’s whole attention. You cannot eliminate the complexity of everything that goes on around the writing task, but you can make sure that it is partitioned and directed to people or processes that are best equipped to deal with it.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>The complex relationship of process and rhetoric</db:title>
<db:para>Process and rhetoric are intimately connected. Above, I divided the complexity of content creation into rhetorical complexity and process complexity. But look again and we see that rhetorical issues pervade the process issues.</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>You have to record the content, manage it, and publish it, potentially to many different audiences and many different media. <db:emphasis>But when you manage content and distribute it to different audiences, what are you doing but ensuring that you are delivering the right rhetoric? Content management is the management of rhetoric.</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>If your organization creates a lot of content, you have to coordinate with everyone else creating content and make sure it all works together and serves the organization’s goals. <db:emphasis>And what makes content work together? It must conform to the same rhetorical rules and goals. Content strategy is the strategy of rhetoric.</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>As your subject matter and your business needs change, you need to figure out how your content needs to change and implement those changes cleanly and efficiently. <db:emphasis>And when you determine which changes are needed and how to make them, what are you managing and changing but rhetoric? The content process is the process of creating, managing, and delivering rhetoric.</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>What happens if you don’t manage the inherent complexity of content creation properly? Complexity cannot be destroyed. It has to go somewhere. If your content lacks needed information, the burden of finding that information falls on your readers. If your readers can’t understand the terms used, read the font chosen, find content to explain an unfamiliar concept, get the information they need when they need it, or tell current information from outdated, that is a failure of rhetoric, and that failure of rhetoric occurred because the process did not ensure that it was properly taken care of by a person or process with the knowledge, skills, and resources to do it properly.</db:para>
<db:para>Another name for the failure of rhetoric is poor content quality. Poor content quality is the direct result of the complexity of content creation not being handled properly within the content producing organization. The only product of the content process is rhetoric. All content problems are rhetoric problems and all rhetoric problems are the result of process problems. To consistently create good rhetoric, you must ensure that every piece of the inherent complexity of content creation is directed to a competent and adequately resourced person or process.</db:para>
<db:para>The relationship between complexity and quality has never been better understood or more important. Some of the defining technology of our age is mind-bogglingly complex, but the most successful products – those considered to have the highest quality and value – partition that complexity successfully, creating simple interfaces not only for consumers but also for those who design and build those products. Without a sophisticated partitioning of complexity throughout the supply chain and the design and manufacturing process, many modern products would be impossible to bring to market.</db:para>
<db:para>But in many organizations, the current tools and processes fail to assign each part of the complexity of content creation to the person or process with the best combination of knowledge, skills and resources to handle it. The result is poor content quality, inefficient processes, and reduced revenue and profitability. The cure is to adopt a partitioning that better handles the complexity the organization is experiencing. Structured writing is a tool for implementing that cure. Note that structure writing is not the cure itself. It a tool for implementing the cure. The cure is the correct distribution of complexity in your organization.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>Complexity is complex</db:title>
<db:para>Correctly managing complexity in your content process is complex. There is no magic elixir that will make all of your content processes disappear and the chances that adopting this years gotta-have-it content technology is not going to magically put all your complexity into the right buckets.</db:para>
<db:para>Structured writing is itself a complex technique and some of the most popular structured writing methods of the day are highly complex. That is not necessarily a bad thing. The aim is not to eliminate complexity altogether – which is impossible – but to partition it so that each part of that complexity is handled by the person or process with the knowledge, skills, and resources to handle it. More complex tools are fine if they help you achieve a better partitioning of complexity. But we can’t ignore the complexity that these tools and techniques bring, nor the way that an improper choice of tools or techniques can end up dumping additional complexity on writers or other people in your content system.</db:para>
<db:para>The aim of this book is to help you achieve a better partitioning of the complexity of your content system in order to improve your rhetoric and make your process more efficient and reliable. It cannot accomplish this without taking due notice of the pitfall and difficulties that come with specific structured writing techniques and tools.</db:para>
<db:para>Whenever I talk about process techniques in this book, I will warn about the pitfalls of that technique holds for rhetoric. Whenever I talk about techniques for supporting rhetoric, I will warn about any pitfall those techniques hold for process. Part of this will involve examining methods I don’t actually recommend, or recommend only in highly selective cases. Some of these techniques are widely used, and I therefore think it is important to point out their pitfalls, if only to answer the question of why the alternate techniques that I do recommend should be chosen instead.</db:para>
<db:para>This may appear to give this book a split personality: part survey, part advocacy for a set of techniques that I think should be much better known and much more widely used. But the truth is, almost all of the techniques described in this book are appropriate for use in some situations. Some are terribly overused, and their use will be critiqued. Some are terribly under used, and their use will be advocated. But my aim is to move us toward balance, not to tilt the scale so much the other way that people are again using techniques and tools that do not fit their needs, circumstances, and resources.</db:para>
<db:para>The optimal partitioning of complexity for your organization is unique to that organization (and may well change over time). The aim of this book is to show you how you can use structured writing techniques to develop the partitioning that is optimal for your organization, not to recommend one form or partitioning over another.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>How this book is organized</db:title>
<db:para>This book is organized into seven parts, as follows:</db:para>
<db:variablelist>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term>Structured Writing Domains</db:term>
<db:listitem><db:para>Describes the four main ways in which formal structure can be applied to content, what I call the four domains of structured writing: the Media, Document, Subject, and Management domains. This lays the foundation for discussing how structure is used to partition complexity through the remaining sections of the book.</db:para></db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term>Process, Rhetoric, and Structure</db:term>
<db:listitem><db:para>Describes how rhetoric can be represented in structured writing and how this affects the partitioning of the content system, and then looks at how rhetorical structure is represented at the level of the individual document and of the information set as a whole, and how authors can adapt to working with rhetorical structures in structured writing.</db:para></db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term>Algorithms</db:term>
<db:listitem><db:para>Describes how the partitioning the content process with structured writing involves handing a lot of content complexity over to algorithms, and looks at the main content processing algorithms used in structured writing, how they affect the partitioning of the content system, and how they work in each of the structured writing domains.</db:para></db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term>Structures</db:term>
<db:listitem><db:para>Describes the specific structures used in structured writing in more detail and looks at how structural issues are handled at every scale from full documents to individual phrases.</db:para></db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term>Languages</db:term>
<db:listitem><db:para>Describes the various forms of markup language (and alternative technologies) use to capture and express content structure, including an overview of some of the major public markup systems like MarkDown, DocBook, and DITA.</db:para></db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term>Management</db:term>
<db:listitem><db:para>Describes how structured writing fits into the larger picture of managing the overall content process and shows how structured writing can enable some important management functions that can be difficult or impossible to implement efficiently with less structured content.</db:para></db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term>Design</db:term>
<db:listitem><db:para>Describes an approach for designing the right content partitioning for your content process and selecting the right tools and technologies to implement it.</db:para></db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
</db:variablelist>
</db:section>
</db:chapter>
