<?xml version="1.0"?>
<db:chapter xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:strings="http://exslt.org/strings" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter.scale">
<db:title>Scale</db:title>
<db:para>All of the algorithms we have discussed so far can be carried out either by humans or by algorithms. Algorithms are much faster than humans, but algorithms have to be designed, written, and maintained, and they don’t have the same capacity as humans to adapt on the fly when conditions warrant it. They also require much more precisely structured inputs than humans, meaning that they require more work from human writers, at least for original content creation. (They may save writers work in all sorts of other ways, as we have seen.)</db:para>
<db:para>How do you determine when it is worth the investment to design structures and algorithms and have your writers write structured documents, rather than having them just execute all the algorithms themselves. Issues of consistency and quality are important considerations here. There are also some information designs that are very costly to develop without the aid of algorithms. However, one of the key factors in making this decision is scale.</db:para>
<db:para>The issue of scale applies to many systems and many activities. A home kitchen does not work like a restaurant kitchen. The restaurant kitchen has multiple work stations as divides the work up among multiple cooks. They prepare ingredients in advance so that when an order comes in, they can prepare it very quickly. All the equipment, planning, and preparation costs money, but it pays off when you have to process a lot of food orders during a busy dinner shift. By contrast, a cook in a home kitchen starts with basic ingredients and does all the steps themselves to prepare a single meal for themselves or a small group.</db:para>
<db:para>The restaurant could not possibly keep up with order if it worked the way a home kitchen worked. That method of preparation does not scale up to the throughput of a restaurant. Equally, though, the approach of a restaurant kitchen would not work for a home kitchen. The overhead of all the stations, the planning, and the advanced preparation would not be economical for preparing a single small meal. The approaches of a large-scale operation do not scale down to a small-scale operation anymore than the approaches of a small-scale operation scale up for a large organization.</db:para>
<db:para>The same is true of writing.</db:para>
</db:chapter>
