<?xml version="1.0"?>
<db:chapter xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:strings="http://exslt.org/strings" version="5.0">
<db:title>Chunks, blocks, topics, and fragments</db:title>
<db:para>A common theme is many structured writing systems is the idea that documents are made up of various types of blocks. This idea affects both how you look at information design and how you look at the creation of data structures and algorithms.</db:para>
<db:para>Information Mapping is a structured writing system which views all content as being made up of just six types of information block: Procedure, Process, Principle, Concept, Structure, and Fact. Every document, according to Information Mapping theory, is made of of blocks of these six types united by a map. Thus in the recipe example we have used frequently in this book, the introduction to the recipe is a concept, the list of ingredients is a structure, and the preparation steps are a procedure. The recipe as a whole is an information map made up of these blocks.</db:para>
<db:para>Information Mapping is a theory about how documents are constructed to convey information, so these block types would count as document domain structures. However they are much more abstract structures than any we have looked at so far, which have mostly been abstract versions of formatting structures like lists and tables.</db:para>
<db:para>DITA also adopts this idea of documents being made up of blocks. In DITA’s case, these blocks are named topics, which leads to some confusion since the word topic can be used to refer to both a block in the Information Mapping sense, which is not a complete document and topic in the sense of a help topic, which is a whole document.</db:para>
<db:para>DITA is commonly associated with the idea that all content is either concept, task, or reference, though DITA actually defines more topic types than this today.</db:para>
<db:para>DITA’s topic types are a little more functionally oriented than Information Mapping’s block types. DITA’s types are based on what the reader is doing -- performing a task, understanding an idea, or looking up information. Information Mapping’s types are more epistemological in nature -- trying to delineate what type of knowledge is being transferred.</db:para>
<db:para>All of this is quite distinct from the subject-based information typing of the subject domain. The instructions in a recipe and a knitting pattern are both tasks in DITA terms and procedures in IM’s terms. But in the subject domain they are distinct types because there is a distinct way in you which write knitting instructions.</db:para>
<!-- EXAMPLE -->
<db:para>DITA and Information Mapping’s approaches are broad and analytical, trying to find commonalities across many different kinds of information. The subject domain is very much specific and synthetic, concerned which how specific pieces go together to successfully describe a particular subject. All three approaches break content up into blocks, and the subject-specific blocks of the subject domain can probably be categorized according to the information typology of either DITA or Information Mapping. However, the specific structured writing structures that you would create in each case are different. Both the Information Mapping and DITA approaches, when reduced to specific markup structures, create abstract document domain structures. The subject domain, of course, creates subject domain structures.</db:para>
<db:para>At the same time, the subject domain is not attempting to define an ontology. It is not trying to capture knowledge in a formal way. It is trying to capture and to shape content in a way that is specific to its subject matter.</db:para>
<db:para>We should be clear that this is not the only view of the structure of a document. We might also see a document as a punctuated flow.</db:para>
</db:chapter>
