<?xml version="1.0"?>
<db:chapter xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:strings="http://exslt.org/strings" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter.three-domains">
<db:title>Introduction</db:title>


<db:section>
<db:title>From ideas to dots</db:title>
<db:para>The process of creating and delivering content consists of translating ideas (stuff someone thinks or knows) into concrete physical form that can be read (dots or lines of ink on a page, or pixels on screen).</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/ideas2dots.svg" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>The writing and publishing process is all about how we get from ideas in a head to dots on a page. Structured writing is about applying a structured methodology to that process. It is a long road from ideas to dot, and structured writing techniques can be applied at many points along that road. Almost all writing done today uses structured writing techniques to one extent of another. As this book will show, the basic principles of structured writing apply across the spectrum, from the tools and techniques used in most offices today, to most sophisticated structured writing systems. It is not a matter of unstructured vs structured approaches, but the degree of structure used.</db:para>
<db:para>All writing has structure in the literary sense of the word. Every comprehensible sentence has a grammatical structure. You may even have learned to diagram that structure in school. <db:footnote><db:para>By Tjo3ya - Own work, CC BY-SA 3.0, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=18312612</db:para></db:footnote></db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/Examples_of_Reed-Kellogg_diagrams.jpg" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>Many texts also have deliberate rhetorical structure: a particular way of assembling words and other media to effectively inform or persuade an audience. Sometimes that rhetorical structure is ad hoc, invented by the writer for a unique individual piece. But often it is repeated for many similar pieces of content. Thus newspapers stories have a repeated rhetorical structure known as the pyramid model, in which the most important facts are promoted to the opening sentences of the pieces. Recipes have a very familiar structure, with and introduction, a list of ingredients, and a list of preparation steps.</db:para>
<db:blockquote>
<db:section>
<db:title>Hard Boiled Eggs</db:title>
<db:para>A hard boiled egg is simple and nutritious. Prep time, 15 minutes. Serves 6.</db:para>
<db:section>
<db:title>Ingredients</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>12xeggs</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>2qt water</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>Preparation</db:title>
<db:orderedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Place eggs in pan and cover with water.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Bring water to a boil.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Remove from heat and cover for 12 minutes.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Place eggs in cold water to stop cooking.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Peel and serve.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:orderedlist>
</db:section>
</db:section>
</db:blockquote>
<db:para>As a writer, you don’t have to stop to think about the rhetorical structure of a recipe: you follow the established pattern. Many other subjects have similarly well known rhetorical patterns used to describe them. These are all examples of structured writing in the rhetorical sense, and it is well known that adherence to sound rhetorical models greatly improves the quality of writing. They do this by constraining writers to follow the established rhetorical pattern.</db:para>
<db:para>This idea of constraints is fundamental to structured writing. Whenever you specify a structure to be followed, you are imposing a constraint. Constraints define what is and is not required or acceptable in a piece of writing. If you have ever been asked to write following a template or a style guide, you have been asked to follow a set of constraints.</db:para>
<db:para>However, the term structured writing today generally means more than following a style guide or template. It usually means the use of computer data formats (most commonly XML) to capture written content so that it can be processed by algorithms. These data structures are also constraints. They require the writer to write content to fit into a set of specific data structures. These mechanical constraints may or may not correspond to the rhetorical constraints of a particular piece of writing. In some cases, the mechanical constraints are there to serve a publishing or content management purpose and may have nothing to do with the rhetorical structure of the wiring. In some cases they may actually interfere with it.</db:para>
<db:para>However, it is also possible to use mechanical structures like this to help improve the rhetorical structure of content. This is the kind of structured writing that this book is about. From this point on, therefore, I am going to use structured writing to mean writing in data structures. As we go on, we will show how those data structures can give greater and greater support to the literary and rhetorical structure of content.</db:para>
<db:para>Just as all writing has at least a basic grammatical structure, all writing on a computer involves creating basic data structures. Thus the only case in which no structured writing techniques are involved in the writing process is when an author writes down their ideas with pen and paper, and gives that paper directly to the reader. In this case, the entire writing process, from an idea in the writer’s head to words on paper takes place in the writer’s head and any constraints that are imposed on the content are captured and imposed by the writer themselves as they inscribe their words with the pen.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/ideas2dotsrecordend.svg" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>It is rare for writers to record their ideas directly in the final physical form these day. For instance, the writer may write in a word processor, edit the text on screen, and press <db:guibutton>Print</db:guibutton> to sent the content to a printer to create the final form that the reader receives. Or they may press <db:guibutton>Send</db:guibutton> and have the final form rendered on someone else’s monitor. Either way, recording the content happens before the final form is created, and the way the content looks when you write may be different from how it looks when the reader sees it in final form. The point at which the content is recorded, in the journey from ideas to dots, has been moved back just a little bit.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/ideas2dotsrecordmid.svg" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>Word processing, desktop publishing software, and various approaches to structured writing all establish a point in this process from ideas to dots where the content will be recorded by the author, and then provide algorithms to complete the movement from that point to dots on a page.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/ideas2dotsroles.svg" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>I’m going to use the word algorithm a lot in this book. An algorithm is a formalized and consistent way to do something. Basically, if you give an algorithm the same inputs, it should always produce the same outputs every time it is is run. Computer software is an encoding of an algorithm that a computer can execute. But an algorithms is not the same thing as a program. An algorithm is a method. A program describes the algorithm to a computer. You do not need to be a programmer to create an algorithm. Nor do you need a computer to execute an algorithm. Human being can execute algorithms as well.</db:para>
<db:para>The reasons I am going to talk about algorithms and not software is that algorithms are fundamental to structured writing. Algorithms and structures work together and you can’t design one without the other. The reason you add structure is to enable algorithms. The heart of this book is a description of the principal structured writing algorithms and the structures that support them. The goal of structured writing is to make content better, and it is the algorithms, not the structures that do that. The structures exist to support the algorithms.</db:para>
<db:para>Constraints play an important role for algorithms. First, they help assure the quality of the data that the algorithms consume by controlling what authors create. Secondly, they constrain the interpretation of the data. In other words, the structures that authors create in the content tell the algorithms what each piece of content means. The more precisely the structures constrain the interpretation of the data, the more the algorithms can do with that data.</db:para>
<db:para>We use structured writing algorithms to help us with the writing process. We use them either to take over or to support parts of the writing task. This usually involves moving the point at which content is recorded earlier in the process from idea to dots, allowing the algorithms more scope to assist in the process. Generally speaking, the more we constrain the creation and interpretation of content with structure, the earlier we can move the point of recording, and the more we can do with the content.</db:para>
<db:para>We can describe this process of earlier recording in terms of three domains, each domain reflecting a stage in the progress from ideas to dots. The domains are the media domain (which is concerned with lines and dots on paper or screen), the document domain (which is concerned with the expression and organization of documents), and the subject domain (which is concerned with the ideas that we write about.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>The three domains</db:title>
<db:para>Let’s suppose that an author is planning to write a recipe for chicken noodle soup. They start out with the idea of a soup made with chicken and noodles. This is an idea about the subject matter and not yet any form of content.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/3d.png" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>They then decide to give the dish the name “Chicken Noodle Soup.” That name is content. However, it is not yet part of a document. It is a piece of data in the subject domain.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/3d_name.png" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>Then the author composes a recipe for Chicken Noodle Soup. They are now composing a document that has structures like a title, a list of ingredients, and a preparation procedure. They use use name of the dish as the title of the recipe. That title is a piece of data in the document domain, but because it is the title of a recipe, it still has a strong association with the subject domain (a recipe is a document with a very specific subject).</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/3d_title.png" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>As the process continues, some format for publishing the recipe is chosen. This might be HTML. HTML is a markup language in the document domain. That is, it contains markup for typical document structures such as titles, paragraphs, and lists. To express the title of the recipe in HTML, we turn the declaration of the title of the recipe into a declaration about an HTML heading level:</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/3d_h1.png" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>This breaks the association of the title with the subject domain. At this stage we are recording that “Chicken Noodle Soup” is the title of a web page, not that it is the title of a recipe, and not that it is the name of a dish. However, we have now specified what type of document this is: a web page.</db:para>
<db:para>If you follow modern practice, your HTML should not include any specific information about how the document will be rendered -- what fonts will be used, how big the margins will be, etc. These things should be specified by a CSS stylesheet.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/3d_css.png" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>Adding the CSS moves the entire package further into the media domain. Notice, however, that in this case, all of the document domain information in the HTML format has been retained. The movement from the subject domain through the document domain into the media domain does not have to mean that information from an earlier domain has to be thrown away as you add information from the later domains. For instance, HTML5 microformats allow you to retain subject domain information all the way into the user’s browser. Traditional publishing techniques tended to throw away subject domain information as the process advanced. Today, that information is more likely to be retained as long as possible. (One of the implications of the term “intelligent content”.)</db:para>
<db:para>When the resulting page is loaded into a browser, dots are painted on the screen in the appropriate shape.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject><db:imageobject><db:imagedata fileref="../graphics/3d_chicken.png" contentwidth="4in" align="left"/></db:imageobject></db:mediaobject>
<db:para>This process involves translating the document and media domain information in the HTML and CSS into the graphics primitives of the platform on which the content is displayed -- basically lighting up dots on a screen or printing dots on paper. This final step will destroy all document and subject domain information, but since the browser retains the HTML source, any information that has reached that point is available to code running in the browser and to other services running on the Web.</db:para>
<db:para>All content passes through the three domains. Content always begins with the author thinking about subjects in the real world. They then decide to express ideas about those subjects in words. They collect their ideas together and determine an order and structure to express them. Finally, they decide how they will be formatted in a particular media. The question is, where in this process that all content goes through does the author start recording the content.</db:para>
<db:para>Where did the author in this scenario actually record their content? They could have recorded it in the subject domain and let an algorithm take it from there. Since the chosen output format is HTML, which is a document domain language, they could not have delayed recording any longer than that. Actually, that’s not entirely true. If they used a graphical HTML editor that allowed them to add styles by hand, they could actually have done their work in the media domain, even if a document domain tagging language was being created under the surface. Of course, if they had been intended to publish the recipe on paper, perhaps just making one copy to give to a friend, they could have delayed recording it until the very end of the media domain. Wherever they recorded it, however, their thought process in creating the finished recipe would have had to go through all three domains.</db:para>
<db:para>An content must pass through all three domains to get from ideas in a head to dots on a page. But the author can record that content in the media domain, the document domain, or the subject domain. In the next three chapters we will look at what it is like to write in each domain.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:chapter>
