<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
<title>The composition algorithm</title>
<annotations>
<p>Concepts</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">media domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">management domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">media-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">document-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">management-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">hybrid tagging language</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Languages</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="language">SAM</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">DITA</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">DocBook</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">Markdown</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">HTML</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Algorithms</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="algorithm">publishing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">publishing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">synthesis algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">synthesis</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">presentation algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">presentation</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">formatting algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">formatting</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">encoding algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">encoding</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">composition algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">composition</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm" specifically="composition">composability</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">separating content from formatting</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single sourcing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single sourcing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">differential single sourcing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">differential single sourcing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single source of truth</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single source of truth algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">reuse</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content reuse</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content reuse algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">reuse algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content management algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content management</annotation></phrase></p>
</annotations>
<p>The composition algorithm deals with the problem of composing a larger work out of smaller pieces. Many traditional writing tools produce files that are meant to encompass a whole work. If you take two Word files, for example, or two FrameMaker files and simply join them together, the result will not be a document that is the combination of the two files, it will be a corrupt file that will not open.</p>
<p>Both Word and FrameMaker have features that allow you to compose Word and FrameMaker documents out of smaller pieces. To a limited extent, they may even allow you to compose documents out of files other than their own. Some systems are specifically designed to allow you to compose document from many different source files. In most cases, though, some cleanup is required before the imported files can be used, particularly if they contain <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> formatting information. This cleanup requirement means that this is usually a one time import. You can’t keep editing the original files and have the changes immediately reflected in the importing system.</p>
<p>Systems that require a high degree of composability have often turned to structured writing for solutions to the composability problem.</p>
<p>There are several parts to the composability problem, each of which structured writing helps address.</p>
<section>
<title>Fundamental composability</title>
<p>The first requirement of composability is that you must actually be able to combine the pieces. Most structured writing formats consist of a hierarchy of structures. Those structures tend to be self similar in form. For instance, all structures in an XML document are composed of XML elements. This means that you can take an XML document apart at any point in the structural hierarchy and insert, remove, or rearrange the structures at that level. To compose a larger structure out of smaller structures, you simply wrap new elements around them.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Structural composability</title>
<p>The second requirement of composability is that the result of combining markup structures must be a valid document (must conform to the appropriate constraints for that document). The simplest way to assure this it to plan all of your pieces to fit the constraints of the documents they will be inserted into. The most obvious way to do this it to make sure that all of your pieces come from the same tagging language. But you must also make sure that the pieces go into a place where they are structurally allowed. Just because all the pieces come from the same languages does not mean that every possible combination results in a valid document. This require planning and careful management to make sure the combinations you create are valid.</p>
<p>However, it is not essential that all the pieces you want to combine come from the same language as the document you are composing. You can also take content from different sources and with different structures, as long as you can transform their structures on input to match the structures of the destination document. This can be a very powerful technique in some cases. For instance, you can use it to compose documents from content in a database. (Indeed, all database reporting systems are exactly this: systems that compose documents in one format from tabular data in another format.) Structural composability depends on the semantic equivalence of structures, not common syntax.</p>
<p>For this approach to work, however, it is important that all of the sources you draw from have a high level of <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance</annotation></phrase> to their structures. If you don’t know, or cannot rely on, the structure of the pieces you are drawing in, you cannot reliably combine them with an algorithm. Since design for <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance</annotation></phrase> is often more about being specific to the writer’s task and knowledge, composability is often best served by creating file formats that do the best job of ensuring conformance from each type of contributor rather than in trying to get everyone to use the same format.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Composition for publication</title>
<p>While structural composability is vital, it is not always sufficient. You could have pieces in a <phrase><annotation type="concept">media domain</annotation></phrase> language that are structurally composable but formatted differently. The resulting document would be valid and would publish successfully, but it would be a mess of competing styles and fonts.</p>
<p>For practical purposes, then, you should not try to create composable content in the <phrase><annotation type="concept">media domain</annotation></phrase>. You should at least use the <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase>. The <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">separates content from formatting</annotation></phrase> so you can compose a document in the <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> and then apply consistent formatting to the result.</p>
<p>This is true even if the pieces are in different <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> languages. All document domain languages essentially describe the same set of abstract document structures -- document are documents after all, they all have the same basic structures which all document domain languages seek to represent. As long as you can recognize the same basic structures in each of the source languages, you can compose a document from pieces in different document domain languages by converting to a common output language. (Embedded management domain markup may spoil the party, however, since there is not the same level of semantic equivalence between management.)</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Literary composability</title>
<p>Even if you can assemble pieces from different document domain sources and format them all with a single consistent look, that does not mean that the result will be a complete, correct, coherent piece of writing.</p>
<p>This is not necessarily a matter of making the document sound like it came from a single person. Many business documents are the result of several different writers, sometimes working together, sometimes inheriting and maintaining a document over time. Truly making such a document sound like it was all written by one person is a tall order and usually not necessary to achieve it business purpose.</p>
<p>What does matter is that the document be cohesive and coherent. The terminology it uses should be consistent from beginning to end. The end should flow logically from the middle and the middle from the beginning. There should not be obvious duplications of content nor omissions (obvious or not). This clearly requires a number of constraints on the content affecting both composition and style.</p>
<p>There are a couple of approach to managing the constraints on composition. One is the information chunking approach that you find in systems like <phrase><annotation type="language">DITA</annotation></phrase> or <phrase><annotation type="system">Information Mapping</annotation></phrase>. In this approach, content is broken down into certain broad types such as procedure, process, principle, concept, structure, and fact (Information Mapping) or task, concept, and reference (DITA -- though DITA allows you to define others though specialization.) The idea here is that if you keep reference information in a separate chunk from a concept, for instance, the chunks will compose more reliably, since there will not be duplicate concept information in a reference chunk.</p>
<p>The difficulties with this approach is that these abstract categories don’t always make a lot of sense to writers when they are writing about concrete subject, and different writers may interpret the chunk types or their boundaries differently, resulting in material that does not compose as well as you might hope.</p>
<p>Also, this chunking approach, while it has been shown to improve the quality of writing in some cases, can also impose and artificial clunkiness and lack of flow on the content, leaving it feeling choppy or disjointed.</p>
<p>The other approach to literary composability is to move content to the <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase>. A subject domain structure for a particular subject does not have to be structured as a collection of abstract chunk types. The structure is highly specific to the subject matter at hand and is therefore much more concrete and less susceptible to varying interpretation by writers. Also, you can use the subject domain to factor out many of the style issue that might otherwise compromise composability. (This is just like factoring out formatting issues by moving from the <phrase><annotation type="concept">media domain</annotation></phrase> to the <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase>.)</p>
<p>Of course, not all material fits into obvious strongly typed <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> structures. Content that is more conceptual or theoretical in nature does not have a strong <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> structure because it does not approach it subject matter in such a systematic or regular way. Then again, the ability to compose such content out of existing pieces is limited. By its very nature such content requires a continuous flow of exposition that is very hard to assemble from pre-written chunks.</p>
</section>
</chapter>
