<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter name ="chapter.extract">
<title>Extract</title>
<annotations>
<p>Concepts</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">media domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">management domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">media-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">document-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">management-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">hybrid markup language</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">Every Page is Page One</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">abstract language</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">information architecture</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept" specifically="top-down information architecture">top-down</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">metadata</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Languages</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="language">SAM</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">DITA</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">DocBook</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">Markdown</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">HTML</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">XML</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Algorithms</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="algorithm">authoring algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">authoring</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm" specifically="composition">composability</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">composition algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">composition</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content management algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content management</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content reuse algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content reuse</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">differential single sourcing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">differential single sourcing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">encoding algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">encoding</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">exchange algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">exchange</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">extract and merge algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">extract and merge</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">formatting algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">formatting</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">linking algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">linking</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">presentation algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">presentation</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">publishing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">publishing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">quality algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">quality</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">relevance algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">relevance</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">rendering algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">rendering</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">reuse algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">reuse</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">separating content from formatting</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single source of truth algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single source of truth</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single sourcing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single sourcing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">synthesis algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">synthesis</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm" specifically="conformance">validation</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Tools</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="tool">content management system</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="tool">Content management systems</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Roles</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="role">information architect</annotation></phrase></p>
</annotations>
<index>
<record>
<type>algorithm</type>
<term>extract</term>
</record>
</index>
<p>A great deal of the content we produce, particularly technical and business content, is essentially a report in human language on the specific features of a product, process, or data set. Much of the data that defines those things is contained in some kind of formal data set, such as a database or software source code.</p>
<p>In a traditional approach to publishing, a large amount of complexity and work is involved in researching and recreating the information in those systems in a content format, and then in trying to keep the resulting content in sync with the original source.</p>
<p>The source data for those systems is, in effect, subject domain content for those products, processes, and data sets. Rather than researching and recreating that content, we can use structured writing techniques to extract information from those sources to create and/or validate content. This partitions and redirects the complexity of dealing with these sources away from authors towards information architects and content engineers who create the algorithms to extract that data and transform it into content.</p>
<section>
<title>Tapping external sources of content</title>
<p>I have talked throughout this book about moving content from the <phrase><annotation type="concept">media domain</annotation></phrase> to the <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> and from the <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> to the <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase>. We have seen the advantages that come from creating content in the <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase>, and we have looked at the processing algorithms that can use <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> content to produce various kinds of publications in different media.</p>
<p>Subject domain content is simply content that is created and annotated in structures that are based on the subject matter rather than on the structure of documents or media. Subject domain structures tell you what the content is about, rather than how it should be published. You can therefore write algorithms that processes it based on what it is about rather than how it is presented. It allows you to transfer and delay decisions about presentation and formatting and have algorithms make those decisions based on the <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> markup.</p>
<p>Any data source that is contained and annotated in <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> structures is a source of subject domain content, whether it was intended to produce content from or not. This includes virtually all databases and quite a bit of software code. It also includes all authored content anywhere available (under an appropriate license) that contains any usable subject domain structures or annotations. All of this is potential material for generating content as part of your overall publishing process. As such, the extract algorithm can work effectively with many other structured writing algorithms.</p>
<p>Perhaps most obviously, extract works with the <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">composition algorithm</annotation></phrase>. Extract  provides new sources of content for the composition algorithm to work with.</p>
<p>As a source of <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> content, the extract algorithm also naturally <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">separates content from formatting</annotation></phrase> and contributes to the <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">differential single sourcing algorithm</annotation></phrase>.</p>
<p>By tapping existing information to build content, the extract algorithm also works hand in hand with the <phrase>normalization</phrase> and <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content reuse</annotation></phrase> algorithms. In fact, it is really the highest expression of reuse, since it not only reuses content in the content system, but information from the organization at large, or even beyond the organization – a process that further reduces duplication within the organization.</p>
<p>Because the extract algorithm taps directly into external sources of information, it is also a great source of information for the <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance algorithm</annotation></phrase>. At one level, it provides a canonical source of information to validate existing content against. At another level, it factors out part of the conformance problem from the authoring function. It transfers the entire responsibility for maintaining the information to the creators of the source you are extracting content from, which is a responsibility they already have. This is yet another example of the power of the subject domain to reuse its structures for many purposes, which illustrates just how much complexity is being partitioned and transfered to the algorithms created by the content engineer or information architect.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Information created for other purposes</title>
<p>There is nothing new, of course, about generating content from database records. Database reporting is a highly important and sophisticated field in its own right and it would be entirely correct to characterize it as a type of structured writing. What sets it apart, largely, from other structured writing practices, is that the databases it reports on serves other business purposes besides being sources of content. An insurance company policy database, for instance, may be used to publish custom benefit booklets for plan participants but it is also used for processing claims. The design of the structures and data entry interfaces of these systems has tended to fall outside the realm (and the notice) of writers and authoring system designers.</p>
<p>This is a pity, because it has often resulted in organizations developing separate processes, tools, and repositories for content creation in which the information already contained in databases is researched, validated, recorded, and managed entirely independently on the content side of the house. Rather than treating code and databases as sources of content, writers treat them as research sources. They look information up in these sources and then go away and write content (in a separate repository) to describe the information from those sources.</p>
<p>The essence of the problem is that many content organizations choose to work in the <phrase><annotation type="concept">media domain</annotation></phrase> or the <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> and have neither the tools not the expertize to bridge the gap to all this material already available in the <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase>. But even when content organizations do extend their efforts into the <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase>, they are often blind to the fact that the <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> content they are proposing to create already exists in the systems of another department.</p>
<p>Another drawback is that content produced from these systems, for instance by a database reporting process, exists in isolation from the rest of the content produced by the organization. Such content can often be quite sophisticated and beautifully formatted and published. But it is the product of an entire structured publishing chain that has to be separately developed and maintained.</p>
<p>In the field of software documentation we see the same pattern in regard to programming language API documentation. Much of the material of an API reference guide is a description of each function, what information is required as input (its parameters or arguments), the information it produces as output, and the errors or exceptions that it can generate. All of this information already exists in the code that implements the function.</p>
<p>API documentation tools such as JavaDoc or Sphinx extract this information from code and comments and turn it into publishable content. This is an application of subject-domain structured writing and the API documentation tools that do this implement an entire structured publishing system, producing final output, often in multiple formats.</p>
<p>And here we see all the same problems again:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>An entire publishing chain is maintained separately from the main content publishing chain.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The content produced from this publishing chain is isolated from all the other content produced by the organization.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Much of the same information is often created and maintained separately in a different repository and tool chain in the form programming guides and/or knowledge base articles.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>There are other cases of entirely separate publishing chains producing information that is isolated from the rest of an organization’s content. Technical support organizations create knowledge bases to answer commonly asked questions. The material in these knowledge bases is technical communication, plain and simple, yet it usually exists in isolation from the product documentation set, even to the extent that users may not be able to search both the documentation and the knowledge base from the same search box. Most users, however, have no way of guessing whether the answer they are looking for is going to be in the docs or the knowledge base (or in the users forum, often yet another independent publishing system).</p>
<p>There are a couple of ways to address these redundancies and the isolation that goes with them. One is to attempt to unify all content authoring and production in a single enterprise-wide system, often with a single set of content structures intended for use across all enterprise departments. However, this is a highly expensive and disruptive approach and tends to create interfaces and structures that are less usable and less specific to various business functions than the ones they replace. It ignores the local complexity of individual groups and subject matter, meaning that complexity gets shoved downstream, eventually to the reader. It also ignores the fact that many of the systems from which we wish to extract content exist for other purposes besides the content that is generated from them. Their subject-domain structures are specific and necessary to the database functions or software code generation they were built for.</p>
<p>Another approach is to leave the subject domain systems in place (and perhaps create more of them) and feed their output into a common <phrase><annotation type="concept">document-domain</annotation></phrase> publishing tool chain. It is a normal part of the <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">publishing algorithm</annotation></phrase> for <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject-domain</annotation></phrase> content to pass through the document domain on its way to <phrase><annotation type="concept">media-domain</annotation></phrase> publication. <phrase>Subject domain</phrase> content, by its nature, is not strongly tied to a particular <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> structure, so integrating many sources of <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> content into a single publishing chain is not particularly onerous. (Specific <phrase><annotation type="concept">management-domain</annotation></phrase> features of certain tool chains make things more complicated, but since the subject domain tends to factor out a lot of the management domain, this is not an insurmountable problem.)</p>
<p>Most enterprise-wide content systems are based on <phrase><annotation type="concept">document-domain</annotation></phrase> languages. (There is, after all, no way to create a single enterprise-wide <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject-domain</annotation></phrase> system, since an enterprise creates content on many subjects.) In principle, a document-domain system should be capable of integrating content from domain-specific subject-domain systems.  Unfortunately, it is not common for either the subject domain systems or the enterprise content systems to be designed with this kind of integration in mind.</p>
<p>Because of this, we sometimes have to find ways to extract content from these sources and feed them into a unified publishing chain. This creates the need for <phrase>extraction algorithms</phrase>.</p>
<p>A common example of the <phrase>extraction algorithm</phrase> is found in API documentation tools such as <phrase>JavaDoc</phrase>. These tools parse application source code to pull out things like the names of functions, parameters, and return values, which it then uses to create the outline, at least, of reference documentation. Essentially, it generates a human language translation of what the computer language code is saying.</p>
<p>How the extraction algorithm works depends entirely on how the source data is structured, but it should usually create output in the subject domain that clearly labels the pieces of information it has culled from the source. For instance, a <phrase>Java</phrase> function definition is a piece of structured content in which the role and meaning of each element is known from the pattern and syntax of the <phrase>Java</phrase> language itself (its grammar):</p>
<codeblock language ="java">
boolean isValidMove(int theFromFile, 
                    int theFromRank, 
                    int theToFile, 
                    int theToRank) {
        // ...body
    }
</codeblock>
<p>This same information can be extracted by an algorithm that knows the grammar of <phrase>Java</phrase> to produce something that looks more like <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> content:</p>
<codeblock language ="sam">
java-function:
    name: isValidMove
    return-type: boolean
    parameters:: type, name
        int, theFromFile
        int, theFromRank
        int, theToFile
        int, theToRank
</codeblock>
<p>This is the same information, but in a different structure. In this structure, however, it is easily accessible by content processes and can then be processed through the rest of the publishing tool chain just like any other content.</p>
<p>Any structured data source that expresses the semantics of its data in a consistent way is a source of subject domain content. We just need to find a way to get at it.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>The diversity of sources</title>
<p>When it comes to drawing content from diverse sources, the term <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single sourcing</annotation></phrase> can mislead us. Single source can lead us to think that it means all source content is kept in a single place. Some vendors of content management systems would like to encourage this interpretation. But a better definition is that each piece of information comes from a single source. That is to say, each piece of information comes from only one source, but there may be many sources, each maintaining different information.</p>
<p>Ensuring that content is only stored once is actually about making sure that the information, and the repository in which it is stored, meets an appropriate set of constraints. The constraints that establish the uniqueness of a piece of content are different for different types of content and different subject matter, so such constraints are better expressed and enforced by systems that are specific to their particular subject matter.</p>
<p>Of course, there can often be trivial differences between the ways in which different bodies within an organization store and manage information that could and should be rationalized. There are all kinds of isolated and ad hoc information stores in most organizations that could potentially be much more efficient and much more accessible, with a degree of rationalization and centralization. But it does not follow at all that absolute centralization into a single system or a single data model is appropriate, useful, or even possible.</p>
<p>The best way to ensure that information is stored once is to have it stored in a system with the right constraints and the right processes for the people who create and manage that information. This may mean that an integrated publishing system will draw from diverse sources of information and content. The ability to extract content from these sources and to merge it with other content for publication is therefore central to an effective strategy.</p>
<p>Still, while this model sounds grand, it also introduces a lot of complexity in terms of its integration and maintenance requirements. The point of the exercise, we should always remember, is to minimize the amount of unmanaged complexity in the system. Integrated system can manage complexity in sophisticated ways, but they introduce their own kinds of complexity that has to be factored into the calculation. Sometimes the optimal solution is less than total integration.</p>
</section>
</chapter>
