<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter name="chapter.foreword">
<title>Foreword</title>
<index>
<row>
<type>concept</type>
<value>structured writing</value>
</row>
<row>
<type>concept</type>
<value>constraints</value>
</row>
<row>
<type>concept</type>
<value>structure</value>
</row>
<row>
<type>concept</type>
<value>markup theory</value>
</row>
<row>
<type>concept</type>
<value>annotation</value>
</row>
</index>
<p>This is a book about structured writing. It proposes a theory of structured writing, by which I mean a breakdown of the ways in which structured writing is useful for getting quality writing done efficiently.</p>
<p>I feel the need right off the bat to make a distinction between a theory of structured writing and a theory of markup design. Most forms of structured writing involve the use of markup languages (though markup languages are not the only way to express the structure of content). Most of the study of markup languages has not focused on their role in facilitating the writing process. Markup design theory largely concerns itself with the representation of the structure and/or meaning of texts. It intended use it to make the texts available for further use of study. From a theoretical standpoint, it is concerned with whether and how markup truly reflects important aspects of the content of the text. In other words, markup is seen principally as an means to annotate the text, not to shape it.</p>
<p>This is a matter of significant concern in the humanities, where the <phrase><citation type="citation" value="http://www.tei-c.org">Text Encoding Initiative</citation></phrase> (TEI) plays an important role in determining standards for representing texts for study. But TEI is not about the writing process. It is not about improving the quality of text. In fact, it tires not to influence or change the text, since the text is the object being studied.</p>
<p>Structured writing, on the other hand, is an attempt to improve what is written. As such, its first concern is to constrain the text, to control what can and cannot be written and how it can be expressed. This sometimes means factoring out part of the text itself. The published document that results from the structured writing process may look and read differently from the structured source from which it was produced. It is a means to shape text, and only incidentally to annotate it.</p>
<p>The biggest consequence of this is that ease of authoring becomes a key design goal. Structured writing aims to make content better. Markup that is hard to use to to understand does not make content better because it distracts the author from the writing task. It may even disqualify the most appropriate author from writing the content at all, if they are not willing or able to learn the system.</p>
<p>At the same time, structured writing does impose constraints on the author. Markup that annotates without constraining does nothing to improve content quality because it provides no guidance and does nothing to detect mistakes or to make content easier to validate and audit. The right constraints help the writer create better content, but they do impose on the author’s attention as they are writing. It is important to make sure that the constraints are congenial if they are not to do more harm than good.</p>
<p>Many existing markup languages show some balance of constraint and annotation in their design. This book aims to provide a systematic way of thinking about structured writing as a system of constraints on the writing process. It will treat markup design as a discipline supporting the expression of such constraints. Markup, for this purpose, is not an end, but a means to an end, which is the creation and delivery of high quality content.</p>
<p>This does not mean that it is unconcerned with markup as annotation, since content delivered as annotated markup is an increasingly important part of publishing on the Web. Highly annotated content may therefore be an important output of a modern structured writing process. This book, however, is not concerned with the theory behind what annotation is desirable in published content, but with how we can constrain the writing process to produce that annotation with the greatest consistency and quality.</p>
<p>I have called this book “Structured Writing”, even though the term “structure content” is more commonly used today. This is deliberate. The focus of this book is on writing, on the point at which, and the process by which, ideas get written down.</p>
<p>Many advocates of structured content talk about it primarily as a stored resource, a corporate content asset. They talk about how structure enhances the value of that asset by allowing it to be used in multiple ways to generate more revenue. This is a good thing, but if we only think of structure this way we can end up designing structures for the sake of repositories and processing algorithms without thinking enough about how the author is going to actually write content into those formats.</p>
<p>Not thinking about the writing process can result in structures that are difficult for authors to create. This divides the author’s attention during the authoring process, which reduces the quality of the writing they do. Equally, it fails to take advantage of the capacity of structured writing techniques to actively improve the quality of content. Thus the system designed to preserve the value of content fails often as a system to create valuable content.</p>
<p>As this book will show, these are not incompatible aims. By focusing on structured writing as a tool for content creation, and for content quality enhancement, we can supply content that meets all of the downstream value extraction needs as well. However, the focus in this book is on the writing process itself, and how we can use structured writing techniques to make authoring easier while improving content quality.</p>
<p>As a term, “structured writing” is part of a cluster of terms that includes “structured authoring,” “structured content,” and, more recently, “intelligent content.” Certain communities prefer one term over the other. Tool vendors, for instance, almost always use “structured authoring.” Many content strategists have recently adopted “intelligent content”.</p>
<p>These terms all have the same center, if not always the same edges. “Intelligent Content,” in particular, seems to imply a particular application of structured writing, rather than being simply a synonym (though if it grows in popularity, the term’s implications will inevitably grow looser). And clearly there is a difference in emphasis between “authoring” (a verb), “content” (a noun), and “writing” (both verb and noun). I am choosing to use “structured writing” for this book because it bridges three concerns - the act of composition (writing as an act) and the act of management (writing -- or content -- as an asset to be managed) and consumption (writing as a product to be consumed).</p>
<p>Some readers may detect something of a split personality in this book. On the one hand, I have very deliberately tried to cover the field of structured writing in an even handed way, and to show both the benefits and costs of the various structured writing techniques. At the same time, I have definite opinions on many topics in structured writing and I cannot pretend that these never influence the things I choose to talk about or the way I characterize them. There is definitely an element of advocacy in this work. I will, from time to time, declare my prejudices as a warning to the reader that the opinions of others on a subject may diverge from my own. I may not do it as often as I should.</p>
<p>Others have their prejudices as well, of course. Much of what is written about structured writing and structured writing systems comes from people who have a vested interest in one particular system or another, either because they are associated with a vendor or consultant whose business is built on a particular model, or because they have training or experience in a particular model and want those skills to continue to be relevant. That does not invalidate what they say, but the reader should be aware the there may be a bigger picture.</p>
<p>I hope that this book will serve to provide an independent language and set of ideas in which the various approaches to structured writing can be discussed in neutral terms, including discussion of, and disagreement with, my own prejudices in the field.</p>
</chapter>
