<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
<title>Foreword</title>
<p>This is a book about structured writing. It proposes a theory of structured writing, by which I mean largely a breakdown of the ways in which structured writing is useful for getting quality writing done efficiently.</p>
<p>I feel the need right of the bat to make a distinction between a theory of structured writing and a theory of markup design. Most forms of structured writing involve the use of markup languages (though markup languages are not the only way to express the structure of content). Most of the study of markup languages, however, has not focused on their role in facilitating the writing process. Markup design theory largely concerns itself with the representation of the structure and/or meaning of texts. It intended use it to make the texts available for further use of study. From a theoretical standpoint, it is concerned with whether and how markup truly reflects important aspects of the content of the text. In other words, markup is seen principally as an means of annotating the text.</p>
<p>Structured writing, on the other hand, is an attempt to mange and control what is written. As such, its first concern is to constrain the text, to control what can and cannot be written and how it can be expressed. This sometimes means factoring out part of the text itself.</p>
<p>This does not mean that structured writing is not interested in annotating content. Annotation can be extremely useful for improving the quality of content. On the Web, annotation can also be important for making content findable and usable by downstream processes. Annotation may therefore be both a tactic and a goal of structured writing. But for structured writing, the amount and type of annotation and/or constraint used is a practical matter. It is not about achieving an abstractly “correct” markup, but about creating better content more efficiently to serve specific purposes.</p>
<p>The biggest consequence of this is that structured writing approaches markup as a tool for authoring. The ease of authoring becomes a key design goal. The basic tools of any craft are a key to quality. Structured content aims to make content better. Markup that is hard to use to to understand does not make content better because it distract the author from the writing task. It may even disqualify the most appropriate author from writing the content at all, if they are not willing to learn the system. Markup that annotates without constraining similarly does nothing to improve content quality because it provides no guidance and does nothing to detect mistakes or to make content easier to validate and audit.</p>
<p>Without the ability to constrain, and therefore to validate, there is also nothing helping to make sure that the annotation of the content is correct.</p>
<p>Many existing markup languages show some balance of constraint and annotation in their design. This book aims to provide a systematic way of thinking about structured writing as a system of constraints on the writing process. It will treat markup design as a discipline supporting the expression of such constraints. Markup, for this purpose, is not an end, but a means to an end, which is the creation and delivery of high quality content.</p>
<p>This does not mean that it is unconcerned with markup as annotation, since content delivered as annotated markup is an increasingly important part of publishing on the Web. Highly annotated content may therefore be an important output of a modern structured writing process. This book, however, is not concerned with the theory behind what annotation is desirable in published content, but with how we can constrain the writing process to produce that annotation with the greatest consistency and quality.</p>
<p>I have called this book “Structured Writing” for a reason, even though the term “structure content” is more commonly used today. This is deliberate. The focus of this book is on writing, on the point at which, and the process by which, ideas get written down.</p>
<p>There is a tendency when we think in terms of structured content to think about the stored resource, the corporate content asset, and how structured enhances the value of that asset by allowing it to be used in multiple ways to generate more revenue. This all a very good thing, but when we think in these terms we often end up creating content structures for the sake of repositories and processing algorithms. We create structures that preserve the value of the content asset for the corporation, but we do so without thinking about how the author is going to actually write content into those formats.</p>
<p>Failure to think about this issue can reduce the quality of your content by dividing the author’s attention during the authoring process. Equally, it fails to take advantage of the capacity of structured writing techniques to actively improve the quality of content. Thus the system designed to preserve the value of content fails as a system to create valuable content.</p>
<p>As this book will show, these are not incompatible aims. By focusing on structure writing as a tools for content creation, and for content quality enhancement, we can supply content that meets all of the downstream value extraction needs as well. However, the focus in this book is on the writing process itself, and how we can use structured writing techniques to make authoring easier while improving content quality.</p>
</chapter>
