<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
<title>Other Preface</title>
<p>You probably have an idea about what structured writing is. The first thought that pops into your head might be DITA or Information Mapping or XML. You might think of it as using <code>&lt;strong&gt;</code> rather than <code>&lt;bold&gt;</code> in HTML. You might think of it as synonymous with topic-based authoring. You may think of it as replacing paragraphs with tables and lists. You may think it has to do with chunking or taxonomy. But these are only instances of structured writing. Structured writing is much bigger than any of these individual instances suggest, and its implications and possibilities are much larger.</p>
<p>Structured writing is a tool that can enable you to change how your entire content process is partitioned, and that can have profound economic consequences for your organization. It can go straight to your bottom line in highly significant ways.</p>
<p>Content looks deceptively simple. A stream of words. A few heading to break it up. Some pictures. Maybe a video or two. Easy-peasy. Publishing looks similarly straightforward: apply a few fonts, tweak the margins. Push the Print button. Done. In practice, though, content is one of the most difficult and complex things that any organization creates. That simple stream of words must actually communicate, actually convince. It must be consistent with the other things we say and how we say them, while avoiding redundancy, error, and omission. Its publication must be consistent, and timely, and appropriate to its media and its audience and the device it is viewed on. And somehow it just never is.</p>
<p>If there is any part of your corporate processes and tools that users hate more than any other, chances are it is your content process and tools. If there is any source of delay in your production process more confounding and mysterious than any other, chances are it is your content process. If there is any part of your public face and outreach that is more difficult to measure, to analyze, or to fix, chances are it is your content. If there is anything that is the hardest for an organization to get its arms around, chances are it is its content.</p>
<p>Content creation often seems to be the most unsystematic, ad-hoc, unreliable, unmeasurable, uncontrollable, process in an organization. It methods and tools are often arcane, and attempts to bring structure and process to the content process often end up making even more arcane, impenetrable, and subject to inexplicable failures and you-cain’t-get-there-from-here roadblocks.</p>
<p>Much of this results from solutions that attack only individual parts of the content process, often creating more problems in the rest of the process than they solve in the parts they attack.</p>
<p>The strategic importance of looking at the role content holistically is increasingly being realized, and this has resulted in the growing role of the <phrase>content strategist</phrase> in many organizations. But this does not in itself address the fragmentation and complexity of the content processes that we find in may organizations, and which stand in the way of implementing and managing a comprehensive content strategy.</p>
<p>Structured writing, if we look at it as a whole, rather than looking only as a specific structured writing technique or tool, can provide the means to attack the overall content process problem and to bring the content process into line with your content strategy. It can do this by attacking the fundamental complexity of the content process.</p>
<p>The way you manage any complex process successfully is to partition it so that every part of the complexity is address by a person or process with the knowledge, time, and resources to handle it correctly. The failures in any complex process can be traced to failures to so direct complexity, resulting in that complexity going unhandled, resulting in poor quality, system failures, and a growing disorder in your data, your process, and your product.</p>
<p>Few of our current content processes and tools take a sufficiently holistic approach to the content process. Few address all the areas of complexity in that process and many actively increase the amount of complexity that falls on key actors in the process, most particularly writers and other content contributors.</p>
<p>This books is for writers, content strategists, information architects, content engineers, web masters, and content owners in organizations that need to take a more comprehensive approach to their content processes in order to more effectively implement their content strategy. It demonstrates how structured writing techniques can be use to change the way your content processes are partitioned to make sure that every aspect of content production is handled by a person or process with the time, skills, and resources to handle it successfully.</p>
<p>The emphasis here is on content quality first and foremost, by which I mean the rhetorical quality of content, its ability to do its job by informing and/or persuading a particular audience in a particular time and circumstance. It also focuses on process efficiency, but it is careful to show where attempts to improve process efficiency can have negative effects on quality and to suggest alternative approaches that preserve and enhance quality while increasing process efficiency.</p>
<p>Content strategy has shown us that we can no longer take a piecemeal ad hoc approach to content. Neither can we afford to keep taking a piecemeal ad hoc approach to content process. This books shows how an appreciation of the full range of structured writing techniques can enable you to implement a truly comprehensive content process that properly manages the complexity of content creation without letting anything fall through the cracks.</p>
</chapter>
