<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface name ="alt-preface">
<title>Preface</title>
<p>Structured writing is often presented at the cure to content silos in an organization. But the world of structured writing is itself a world of silos consisting of individual structured writing systems of various levels of complexity and capability, each with its own vocabulary, its own tools, and its own fan base. There are the heavyweights like DITA, DocBook, and S1000D; the lightweights like MarkDown, ReStructuredText, and ASCIIDoc; the niche players, like JavaDoc and LaTeX; the technical tools, like XML, YAML, and JSON, and the structural theories like InformationMapping. But while there is certainly some commerce between these worlds, there is not a great deal of mutual understanding, and to many people working in the field, their particular silo is the whole of structured writing. Thus for may structured writing means DITA and nothing else. For others, it means Information Mapping and nothing else.</p>
<p>Almost nowhere will you find advocacy of structured writing in its own right. It will almost always be advocacy of one of its silos, of one language or another, one standard or another, one tool or another, often presented as the panacea that cures all content ills.</p>
<p>This situation is a huge impediment to the further development of content practices for organizations of all sizes. The scope of capability offered by structured writing as a whole greatly exceeds the capabilities of any one system, and the siloed nature of the structured writing space limits not only capability but the understanding of possibilities and thus the ability to make optimal choices.</p>
<p>This book breaks down the silos of the structured writing world by providing an overall explanation of what structured writing is and what it is capable of. It frames structured writing as a way to partition the complexity of any content process to make sure that everything is handled by the person or process with the skill, knowledge, and resources to handle it. It frames this in terms of the two key performance goals of any content process: the creation of consistent high-quality content, and the efficient use of time and resources.</p>
<p>All too often, structured writing is presented or adopted as a cost saving measure with little or no thought given to the maintenance or improvement of quality. Often the result is a breakdown of quality in the face of the increased complexity of the system and under the pressure of constraints that are not related to quality and sometimes inimical to it. Ironically, this often leads to the loss of the sought-for cost savings as writers work around the system to try to maintain the quality that has been lost.</p>
<p>The need to break down the silos of the structured writing world has never been more urgent. As information sets become large, more integrated, more active, and more volatile, the ability to keep up, to manage everything, and, above all, to maintain quality while working at an ever increasing pace, becomes ever more important.</p>
<p>Despite these urgent requirements, there is disillusionment with structured writing in many quarters, often born of unhappy experiences in one of the structured writing silos. But if we look at structured writing as a whole, it is possible to create structured writing environments that handle the challenges of a modern content organization while enhancing quality and providing a greatly simplified authoring experience for all contributors and a more robust and effective management experience for all content owner and managers.</p>
<p>The aim of this book is to break down the silo of the structured writing world, to provide a framework for understanding the possibilities and methodologies of structured writing as a whole, and to show where some of the major structured writing silos fit in that picture today.</p>
<p>Whether you are living and working in one of the structured writing silos today, are contemplating a move to structured writing or one of it silos, or are simply looking for a way to improve your content process and the quality of the content you produce, this book will show you what is possible, help you understand were your present tools and processes fit in the structured writing landscape, and help you figure out where you want to go next.</p>
</preface>
