<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface name="preface">
<title>Process and Rhetoric</title>
<p>The owners, managers, and producers of content have two fundamental concerns: process and rhetoric. Rhetoric deals with how effective your content is in meeting your goals. Process deals with how effectively and efficiently you produce rhetoric.</p>
<p>Structured writing is a set of techniques that can help you improve your process and your rhetoric. Often, process and rhetoric are treated as separate concerns. It is the thesis of this book that they are, in fact, inseparable, and that structured writing, properly applied, can enhance process and rhetoric at the same time, and thus deliver enormous business value to any organization that produces content.</p>
<p>I am using the word rhetoric in a broad sense here to encompass every aspect of writing that persuades, informs, entertains, or enables the reader to act. The word rhetoric is sometimes use dismissively, to describe content that is hollow or empty of meaning: “mere rhetoric”. And content can certainly use all kinds of rhetorical techniques while entirely lacking substance. But if there can be mere rhetoric there can also be substantive rhetoric, and if you want to communicate your substance effectively, you need sound rhetoric. Rhetoric without substance lacks value. Substance without rhetoric hides value. Substance plus rhetoric unlocks value. If you supply the substance, structured writing can help you to produce sound rhetoric and to do so consistently and efficiently.</p>
<p>It does this in two principle ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>First, it allows you to design your process in ways that direct the complexities of the overall content management and publishing chores away from writers, giving them more time to focus on rhetoric.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Second, it allows you to model and constrain good rhetorical structures, ensuring that you consistently produce the highest quality of rhetoric based on all you know about your readers and their needs.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Too often, structured writing systems and implementations focus on process issues alone, leaving rhetoric to take care of itself. But there are three problems with this approach:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Rhetoric is a complex task requiring the whole of the writer’s attention. Yet many of the tools designed to support process goals such as publishing and reuse introduce numerous complex tasks and concepts into the writer’s environment, pulling attention away from the rhetoric that ought to be their chief concern. This book will show how you can remove most of these distractions from writers using the right techniques.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Some of the structures and processes enforced to meet process goals may be actively harmful to rhetoric. They may make the process more efficient, but at the price of preventing writers from producing the best rhetoric, thereby reducing the quality and effectiveness of content. Fortunately, as this book will show, there are structured writing techniques that can achieve most of the same process goals without harming rhetoric, or while actively improving it. In many cases they also improve the process as well.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>There are large deficits in rhetoric in many content sets that exist because producing first class, thorough, consistent rhetoric is a difficult task in its own right. (The principal cause of this is the Curse of Knowledge, a concept I will explore in <citation type = "nameref" value = "chapter.quality"/>). This book will show how structured writing techniques can be used to address the difficulties and complexities of creating good rhetoric consistently across a body of content.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Process and rhetoric, therefore, should never be treated independently of each other. The whole purpose of the content process is to produce good rhetoric. It is, if you like, a rhetorical process. Process and rhetoric are too intimately connected to hope to successfully treat one while ignoring the other.</p>
<p>This cuts both ways, of course. The things you do to support rhetoric must also be compatible with or contribute too efficient process. An approach to rhetoric that brings your production schedule to a halt is not doing anyone any good. Indeed, timeliness has become one of the key attributes of good rhetoric today. Readers expect information be to available when they need it and to be continually up to date. If your process cannot produce good rhetoric in a timely manner, it is not producing good rhetoric at all.</p>
<p>Whenever I talk about process techniques in this book, I will warn about the pitfalls of that technique holds for rhetoric. Whenever I talk about techniques for supporting rhetoric, I will warn about any pitfall those techniques hold for process. Part of this will involve examining methods I don’t actually recommend, or recommend only in highly selective cases. Some of these techniques are widely used, and I therefore think it is important to point out their pitfalls, if only to answer the question of why the alternate techniques that I do recommend should be chosen instead.</p>
<p>This may appear to give this book a split personality: part survey, part advocacy for a set of techniques that I think should be much better known and much more widely used. But the truth is, almost all of the techniques described in this book are appropriate for use in some situations. Some are terribly overused, and their use will be critiqued. Some are terribly under used, and their use will be advocated. But my aim is to move us toward balance, not to tilt the scale so much the other way that people are again using techniques and tools that do not fit their needs, circumstances, and resources.</p>
<p>I have been in the structured writing industry for nearly 25 years. In that time I have worked with and designed structured writing systems that improved both process and rheotic. I have also built tools and systems myself (some of which I will talk about in this book), because I have often felt that existing tools did not do enought to balance the demands of process and rhetoric, or to fully exploit the capacity of structured writing to promote both.</p>
<p>Failure to realize the full potential of structured writing may, indeed, be a bigger issue than failure to get the balance right in the tools and systems that are produced and implemented. In the age of the Web, organizations are producing and delivering ever more content on ever shorter deadlines. To keep up and maintain quality, they need tools and techniques that support rapid and reliable delivery of consistent high quality rhetoric.</p>
<p>One of the things I have learned over my career is just how much our minds tend to follow the ruts laid down by our familiar tools and processes. I can’t count the number of requirements documents I have read over the years that insisted that any new system must work exactly like the old system in almost every particular. I don’t believe this is so much a reluctance to change as simply a difficulty imagining how things can be done differently. Making sure that a new system does everything you need doing often means specifying that it does everything the way you are doing it now.</p>
<p>Every tool we use encapsulates a methodology, a set of choices about how a problem should be partitioned and addressed. If we learn a job using one tool, we tend to learn the partitioning and methodology of that tool as if it were the partitioning and methodology of the craft itself. Thus individual tools create ruts in the mind, constraining our ideas about how things are done.</p>
<p>It has been my particular privilege and opportunity to work some of those rare people whose minds seem to be immune to such ruts, and who were able to jog me out of my own ruts, to help me see how different approaches could be both simpler and more effective. To name a dozen would be to neglect a score, but one name in particular deserves mention: Sam Wilmott, principle architect of the OmniMark programming language and all round markup language savant. Sam taught me to see the relationship of text and algorithms in a fundamentally new light and everything I have done in my career leading up to the writing of this book has been working out the implications of what I learned from Sam. The SAM markup language I use for most of the examples in this book is an homage to Sam, and not just in its name.</p>
</preface>
