<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
<title>Markup SAM</title>
<by>Mark Baker</by>
<p>SAM (Semantics Authoring Markdown) is a <phrase><annotation type="concept">hybrid markup language</annotation></phrase> that I created because I got frustrated writing in XML and because I want to write in the subject domain and all the other <phrase><annotation type="concept">concrete markup languages</annotation></phrase> and <phrase><annotation type="concept">hybrid markup languages</annotation></phrase> I can find are principally or wholly document domain languages. Also, I don’t know of any hybrid languages that are <phrase><annotation type="concept" specifically="constraints">constrainable</annotation></phrase>, and I wanted a hybrid language that is constrainable. (Again, because I want to work in the subject domain where constraints are particularly important.) This book is written in SAM.</p>
<p>SAM is the language used for the majority of the examples in this book. I have not explained it fully until now because SAM is designed to make structured clear and that is all I have needed to do in most examples. Naturally, to write in SAM you would need to know more about the rules, but you should be able to read a typical SAM document and understand its structure with little or no instruction.</p>
<p>This is similar, but not identical, to the aim of mainstream concrete and hybrid languages such as <phrase><annotation type="language">Markdown</annotation></phrase> and <phrase><annotation type="language">Restructured Text</annotation></phrase>, which is to have the source file be readable as a document. In other words, they strive to make the document structure clear from the markup. They are document domain languages, and they strive to make sure the the markup expresses the document structure they create in a way that is readable.</p>
<p>SAM has the same goal, except that SAM was designed for creating subject domain languages. As such, it is designed to make the subject domain structure of the document clear to the reader. A SAM document may not look as much like a finished document as a <phrase><annotation type="language">Markdown</annotation></phrase> or <phrase><annotation type="language">reST</annotation></phrase> document. For example, it does not use underlines to visually denote different levels of header. Instead, it focuses on creating a hierarchy of named blocks and fields. In many ways it is similar to a markup language called <phrase><annotation type="language">YAML</annotation></phrase>, which is designed for data rather than documents.</p>
<p>Here is an example of YAML courtesy of Wikipedia:</p>
<codeblock language="YAML">
receipt:     Oz-Ware Purchase Invoice
date:        2012-08-06
customer:
    first_name:   Dorothy
    family_name:  Gale

items:
    - part_no:   A4786
      descrip:   Water Bucket (Filled)
      price:     1.47
      quantity:  4

    - part_no:   E1628
      descrip:   High Heeled "Ruby" Slippers
      size:      8
      price:     133.7
      quantity:  1

bill-to:  &amp;id001
    street: |
            123 Tornado Alley
            Suite 16
    city:   East Centerville
    state:  KS

ship-to:  *id001

specialDelivery:  &gt;
    Follow the Yellow Brick
    Road to the Emerald City.
    Pay no attention to the
    man behind the curtain.
</codeblock>
<p>Key features of YAML are the use of names ending in colons to introduce blocks, and the use of indentation to indicate the hierarchy of the document. SAM uses the same principle.</p>
<codeblock language="SAM">
sam:
examples: Basic SAM structures

    example: Paragraphs
        The is a sample paragraph. It is inside
        the {block}(structure) called `example`.
        It contains two {annotations}(structure),
        including this one. It ends with a blank
        line.

        This is another paragraph.

    example: Lists

        Then there is a list:

        1. First item.
        2. Second item.
        3. Third item.

    example: Block quote

        Next is a block quote with a {citation}(structure).

        """[Mother Goose]
            Humpty Dumpty sat on a wall.

    
    </codeblock>
</chapter>
