<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter name="chapter.subject-domain">
<title>Writing in the Subject Domain</title>
<annotations>
<p>Concepts</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">media domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">management domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">media-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">document-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">management-domain</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">hybrid tagging language</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">Every Page is Page One</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">abstract language</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">information architecture</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept" specifically="top-down information architecture">top-down</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="concept">metadata</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Languages</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="language">SAM</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">DITA</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">DocBook</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">Markdown</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">HTML</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="language">XML</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Algorithms</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="algorithm">authoring algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">authoring</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm" specifically="composition">composability</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">composition algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">composition</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conformance</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content management algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content management</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content reuse algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">content reuse</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">differential single sourcing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">differential single sourcing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">encoding algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">encoding</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">exchange algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">exchange</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">extract and merge algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">extract and merge</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">formatting algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">formatting</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">linking algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">linking</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">presentation algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">presentation</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">publishing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">publishing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">quality algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">quality</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">relevance algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">relevance</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">rendering algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">rendering</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">reuse algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">reuse</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">separating content from formatting</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single source of truth algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single source of truth</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single sourcing algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">single sourcing</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">synthesis algorithm</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">synthesis</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="algorithm" specifically="conformance">validation</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Tools</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="tool">content management system</annotation></phrase> <phrase><annotation type="tool">Content management systems</annotation></phrase></p>
<p>Roles</p>
<p><phrase><annotation type="role">information architect</annotation></phrase></p>
</annotations>
<index>
<title>type, term</title>
<p>concept, subject domain</p>
</index>
<p>Structured writing in the <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> means creating structures that are specific to the subject matter being discussed. Sometimes the use of the subject domain is a minor part of a primarily <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> language. For example, <phrase><annotation type="language">DocBook</annotation></phrase> includes subject domain tags like <phrase><annotation type="structure" namespace="DocBook">GUILabel</annotation></phrase> for references to part of a computer display. Sometimes it takes the form of a document type that is specific to one subject such as a recipe, a used car review, a tide table, or a travel itinerary. These may be document oriented or subject oriented. A document-oriented subject specific language is designed to specify how a document on that subject should be organized and presented. A subject-oriented subject-specific language factors out organization and presentation details and to capture information about the subject that could be presented in many different ways.</p>
<p>A recipe is a useful example for examining these differences. Notice that the word recipe itself has two meanings. It can mean the formula for a dish. It can also mean the document that records that dish. This reflects a distinction that is important in the subject domain: recording the subject itself, vs creating a document on the subject. We will examine this distinction in this chapter. To begin with, though, we will look at what a recipe looks like in a generic <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> language (one this is not specific to the subject of food preparation).</p>
<p>Here is a recipe written in <phrase><annotation type="language">reStructuredText</annotation></phrase>, a lightweight general purpose markup language:</p>
<figure>
<codeblock language="reStructuredText">
Hard Boiled Eggs
================
A hard boiled egg is simple and nutritious. 
Prep time, 15 minutes. Serves 6.

Ingredients
-----------
    ======  ========
    Item    Quantity
    ======  ========
    eggs    12
    water   2qt
    ======  ========
    
Preparation
-----------
    1. Place eggs in pan and cover with water.
    2. Bring water to a boil.
    3. Remove from heat and cover for 12 minutes.
    4. Place eggs in cold water to stop cooking.
    5. Peel and serve.
</codeblock>
</figure>
<p>In <phrase><annotation type="language">reStructuredText</annotation></phrase>, a line underlined with equals signs is a major heading and one underlined with dashes is a minor heading. A table is created by using equals signs to mark the beginning and end of the table and the boundary between the table head and the table body. Rows are separated by new lines and columns by spaces in the rows of equals signs. Numbered lists are created by putting numbers in front of lines of text. The equivalent HTML document would look like this:</p>
<codeblock language="HTML">
&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Hard Boiled Eggs&lt;/h1&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;A hard boiled egg is simple and nutritious. 
    Prep time, 15 minutes. Serves 6.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h2&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;thead&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;th&gt;Quantity&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;/thead&gt;
        &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;eggs&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;water&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;2qt&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Place eggs in pan and cover with water.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Bring water to a boil.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Remove from heat and cover for 12 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Place eggs in cold water to stop cooking.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Peel and serve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</codeblock>
<p>This document follows the normal constraints of a recipe. That is, it has the things a recipe normally has, in the order they normally occur in a recipe: introduction, list of ingredients, preparation steps. However, it does not record the fact that it follows any of these constraints. Nor would any of these constraints be present to guide the authors while writing. Moving this document to the subject domain means imposing and recording those constraints. Neither <phrase><annotation type="language">reStructuredText</annotation></phrase> nor <phrase><annotation type="language">HTML</annotation></phrase> give us a way to do that, so we will need a different markup language. Here’s what that might look like:</p>
<codeblock language="sam">
recipe: Hard Boiled Egg
    introduction:
        A hard boiled egg is simple and nutritious. 
        Prep time, 15 minutes. Serves 6.
    ingredients:
        * 12 eggs
        * 2qt water
    preparation:
        1. Place eggs in pan and cover with water.
        2. Bring water to a boil.
        3. Remove from heat and cover for 12 minutes.
        4. Place eggs in cold water to stop cooking.
        5. Peel and serve.
</codeblock>
<p>This structure breaks the document up into a collection of named structures. Those structures are “introduction”, “ingredients”, and “preparation” and they are contained in an overall structures called “recipe”. Some of these structures are more subject oriented than others. “recipe” and “ingredients” are particularly focused on the subject of food preparation. “introduction” is a pretty generic <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> structure, and “preparation” is somewhere in the middle.</p>
<p>This simple structure expresses the basic constraint of the well known recipe pattern and records that the author has followed it. One of the common patterns of structured writing is the factoring out of invariants. One of the invariants of the recipe pattern is that it has sections titled “Ingredients” and “Preparation” (or words to that effect). Notice that these titles been factored out here. Since we have structures specifically for <phrase><annotation type="code">ingredients</annotation></phrase> and <phrase><annotation type="code">preparation</annotation></phrase> we can factor out the actual titles and have the presentation algorithm add them in the transformation to the document domain.</p>
<p>If your organization publishes a lot of recipes, you probably have a lot more constraints on the content of your recipes. For instance, you might have a constraint that every recipe must state its preparation time and the number of people it serves. In our subject domain markup, we can enforce and record that constraint by moving the information from the introduction section to separate fields:</p>
<codeblock language="sam">
recipe: Hard Boiled Egg
    introduction:
        A hard boiled egg is simple and nutritious.
    ingredients:
        * 12 eggs
        * 2qt water
    preparation:
        1. Place eggs in pan and cover with water.
        2. Bring water to a boil.
        3. Remove from heat and cover for 12 minutes.
        4. Place eggs in cold water to stop cooking.
        5. Peel and serve.
    prep-time: 15 minutes
    serves: 1
</codeblock>
<p>Enforcing and recording these additional fields not only makes sure your recipes consistently meet your organization’s constraints, they also offer some interesting publishing possibilities. For instance, with this markup in place, you could easily query your set of recipes to create a cookbook of recipes you can make in 30 minutes or less.</p>
<p>Does this mean that the preparation time will now be displayed as separate fields in the output, rather than in-line? Not necessarily. It might be a good idea to call it out in separate fields so that readers can find the information more easily, but if you really wanted that information at the end of the introduction in every recipe, it would be a simple matter for the <phrase>presentation  algorithm</phrase> (see <citation type="nameref" value="chapter.publishing"/>) to construct the sentences “Prep time, 15 minutes. Serves 6.” from the <phrase><annotation type="code">prep-time</annotation></phrase> and <phrase><annotation type="code">serves</annotation></phrase> field values.</p>
<p>In other words, <phrase><annotation type="code">prep-time</annotation></phrase> and <phrase><annotation type="code">serves</annotation></phrase> are pure <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> structures that do not specify presentation at all. Elements of of recipe structure do still specify presentation, though. As we noted, the reStructuredText version above specify a table presentation for the ingredients. Our recipe structure currently specifies a simple list. The block that contains it is labeled “ingredients”, but the contents of the block is just an ordinary unordered list.</p>
<p>There is a relevant constraint here, one which authors need to follow, but one that our markup does not yet impose or record: how to express ingredients. The specification of ingredients in a recipe generally requires three pieces of information, the name of the ingredient, the quantity, and the unit of measure used to express this quantity. These can be presented as a list or a table. To factor out the presentation choice, we can create an ingredient structure that calls out each piece of information separately:</p>
<codeblock language="sam">
ingredients:
    ingredient: 
        name: eggs
        quantity: 12
        unit: each
    ingredient:
        name: water
        quantity: 2
        unit: qt
</codeblock>
<p>There are some shortcuts we can take to make this markup less verbose. (This is a markup language named SAM that I will talk about later):</p>
<codeblock language="sam">
ingredients:: ingredient, quantity, unit
    eggs, 12, each
    water, 2, qt
</codeblock>
<p>By adding and recording these constraints, we get similar benefits as before. We can better enforce any constraints we have about how ingredient lists are structured and formatted, and we gain access to the specific data involved, meaning, for example, that we could write an algorithm to convert our units from imperial to metric for publication in markets where metric units are preferred.</p>
<section>
<title>A key difference between subject and document domains</title>
<p>At this point we can see that with subject domain markup, we have a lot of choices about how documents are constructed. This highlights an important difference between document domain and subject domain markup. A document domain markup language specifies the content and order of a document. We expect that the document domain markup will specify exactly what content is to appear on the page and in what order. This is necessary in the document domain because the document domain does not record any information about the specific subject matter of individual pieces of text. We can’t write an algorithm to publish certain pieces of a document domain file, because the markup does not record which are which. (More on this in the next chapter.)</p>
<p>Once we introduce subject domain markup, however, that changes. With subject domain markup in place, we can write algorithms that select certain pieces of the content to display or not display. This means that the recorded content no longer specifies exactly what content is to appear on the eventual rendered page and in what order. Rather it is a collection of identifiable pieces of content that you can select from or reorder for publication.</p>
<p>Let’s suppose we run a publishing company that publishes a number of magazines. We want to create a common store of recipes for use in all the magazines. But different magazines have different requirements. <phrase><annotation type="italic">Wine Weenie</annotation></phrase> magazine needs to have a wine match with every recipe. <phrase><annotation type="italic">The Teetotaler's Trumpet</annotation></phrase>, naturally, wants a non-alcoholic suggestion.</p>
<p>Here is how that might be handled in the document domain:</p>
<codeblock language="xml">
&lt;section publication="Wine Weenie"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Wine match&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pinot Noir&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section publication="The Teetotaler's Trumpet"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Suggested beverage&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lemonade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</codeblock>
<p>This is an example of what we call <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">conditional text</annotation></phrase>. The “publication” attribute says, display this text only in this publication. (This makes it <phrase><annotation type="concept">management metadata</annotation></phrase>, which we will talk about later.)</p>
<p>By contrast, this is how this might be handled in the subject domain:</p>
<codeblock language="xml">
&lt;wine-match&gt;Pinot Noir&lt;/wine-match&gt;
&lt;beverage-match&gt;Lemonade&lt;/beverage-match&gt;
</codeblock>
<p>This markup says nothing about which documents should contain either of these pieces of information. Nor does it contain the subheadings what would introduce either of them in the appropriate publication. All these decisions are now left to algorithms. This allows us to do far more things with this content without having to rewrite the source files in any way.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Using subjects to establish context</title>
<p>In <citation type="nameref" value="chapter.document-domain"/>, we noted that we can use context to identify the role that certain structures play in a document, which allows us to get away with fewer structures. For instance, we can use a single title tag for all titles because we can tell what kind of title each one is from the context in which it occurs. The same is true with subject domain structures. They can provide context that allows us to treat basic text structures differently.</p>
<p>Consider our markup language for recipes:</p>
<codeblock language="sam">
recipe: Hard Boiled Egg
    introduction:
        A hard boiled egg is simple and nutritious.
    ingredients:: ingredient, quantity, unit
        eggs, 12, each
        water, 2, qt
    preparation:
        1. Place eggs in pan and cover with water.
        2. Bring water to a boil.
        3. Remove from heat and cover for 12 minutes.
        4. Place eggs in cold water to stop cooking.
        5. Peel and serve.
    prep-time: 15 minutes
    serves: 6
</codeblock>
<p>With the ingredients, we saw that we needed to add additional structure to factor out whether the ingredients would be presented as a list or a table. For the preparation, the steps are currently marked up as a numbered list.  Suppose we want to present the steps as steps, rather than just as a generic numbered list (for instance, by labeling them as <phrase><annotation type="bold">Step 1.</annotation></phrase>, etc, rather than just <phrase><annotation type="bold">1.</annotation></phrase>). Do we need to create an additional <phrase><annotation type="code">step</annotation></phrase> structure to do this? Not necessarily. In this case we can can tell the difference between an ordinary ordered list and a set of preparation steps based on context. We can write a rule in the <phrase><annotation type="algorithm">presentation algorithm</annotation></phrase> that creates special formatting just for ordered lists that are the children of <phrase><annotation type="code">preparation</annotation></phrase> elements that are children of <phrase><annotation type="code">recipe</annotation></phrase> elements (just as we could create rules to format a nested list differently from its parent list based on its context).</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Limits of Subject Domain Markup</title>
<p>While all content is specific to its subject matter, not all content breaks down into such easily identifiable fields as a recipe. A generic essay document format fits equally well for an essay on radishes as an essay on asteroids. Subject-specific structures are much easier to discern for reference works. The format of a telephone directory, an API reference, or a parts list is always specific to the subject matter. In fact, we find that the format of an API reference for one programming language can be different from the format of another language because of differences between the languages.</p>
<p>On the other hand, there are many document types that today are typically written as unstructured text, the content of which could be separated into distinct fields, just as we separated prep time and number served into distinct fields in our recipe example. Developing and applying subject domain templates the pull out this content into distinct and accessible fields can serve to make the content more consistent, more accessible to the reader, and more adaptable for various publishing scenarios. We will look at some examples in later chapters.</p>
<p>Most <phrase><annotation type="concept">document domain</annotation></phrase> languages include some subject domain structures. Often they are quite small, sometimes marking up only individual phrases. In most cases, they are optional features, which means they don’t impose much in the way of constraints. Often they are used to factor out certain formatting or presentation decisions.</p>
<p>In other cases, we find document domain languages that are entirely subject specific. They dictate how a document about a particular subject should be written. They have large subject domain structures, often acting like document templates. In many cases, the smaller structures within these template sections are generic document structures that control how the section is to be presented, rather than expressing exactly which pieces of information are to be included, leaving it to the author to determine what the content of a section will contain.</p>
<p>Finally, there are predominantly <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> languages which largely factor out the presentation decisions and specify in detail the information to be included. These languages are the most constrained but they also open up the content to the widest variety of uses as they are effectively miniature databases of subject information that algorithms can query for all kinds of purposes.</p>
<p>You cannot put all of your content into these highly constrained and highly specific <phrase><annotation type="concept">subject domain</annotation></phrase> languages. But for the content that is suitable for this treatment, the benefits can be enormous, both for the quality of your content and the efficiency of your process. We will see several examples of the potential of these kinds of languages as we look at the structured writing algorithms in <citation type="nameref" value="part.algorithms"/>.</p>
</section>
</chapter>
